(Narrator) I think in some ways,
the skyline of a city
can be compared to a human face,
that you can read into those features,
an enormous amount
of the city's personality.
- New York is a city of tall buildings,
that's its essential identity.
- The Twin Towers
were limited in many ways,
but they were maximum skyline.
And for a lot of people,
they were part
of orienting yourself in New York,
'cause you could see them
from almost everywhere.
And with it gone, you feel that loss
and I think in the end,
it's a struggle for New York
to get its city back.
♪ [Everything Is Broken by Bob Dylan] ♪
♪ Broken lines broken strings ♪
♪ Broken threads broken springs ♪
♪ Broken idols broken heads ♪
♪ People sleeping in broken beds ♪
16 ACRES
♪ Ain't no use jiving ♪
♪ Ain't no use joking ♪
♪ Everything is broken ♪
♪ Broken bottles broken plates ♪
♪ Broken switches broken gates ♪
♪ Broken dishes broken pots ♪
♪ Streets are filled with broken hearts ♪
♪ Broken words never meant to be spoken ♪
♪ Everything is broken ♪
- [Scott Raab] New York City's response
to 9/11 and the immediate aftermath,
was exemplary. It was just--
I think wonderful, in terms of people
genuinely opening their hearts
and literally, in many cases,
embracing each other. People who had
nothing in common except geography,
suddenly realizing they had everything
in common and they were a family.
One community.
And I think that's fantastic.
And I think it felt great at the time.
You know, it didn't last forever.
It wasn't ever going to last forever.
It would be nice, you know,
to have that Kumbaya moment,
just go on and on and on and on,
ain't gonna happen,
ain't ever gonna happen,
and it ain't ever gonna happen here.
[loud horn]
Here you have perhaps the most valuable
16 acres on the face of the earth.
And suddenly, it's gone.
And these 16 acres at the center
of the Cosmos, are empty.
And fair game, what fills that vacuum,
depends on who you are.
And the tug of war began immediately.
- [Reporter] "Less than two months ago,
Larry Silverstein's real estate company
spent more than 3 billion dollars to lease
the World Trade Center Towers
for 99 years.
Last Tuesday, he not only suffered
a professional loss
when the landmark buildings
came crashing down,
but a personal one as well.
Several of his employees
are among the missing.
- [Larry Silverstein] I've had the most
gut wrenching experience of my life.
And to lose, for my people, their families,
the devastation that's been wrought
to that part of Manhattan.
- [Reporter] Many people see
that site now
really as hollowed ground
because there are thousands of bodies
that are entombed there.
I mean, should we build
a structure on that site?
-Well, I believe we should.
[phone ringing]
Hello. Oh hey, David. How are you?
- [Philip Nobel] Larry Silverstein
was vilified immediately
as the greedy developer,
because people in New York
don't know any other kind of developer.
- [Silverstein] It wouldn't surprise me,
if the replacement of the
Twin 110-storey towers
ultimately results in the
creation of four towers.
Perhaps, 50, 55--
maybe 60 storeys in height.
- [Philip] The first thing he did was
he came out with a plan for the site.
A kind of a sketch plan for the site
that rebuilt all of the square footage
to the inch and then
threw in a little park.
And that was a week after the attack.
You know, too early.
Then, he told the Wall Street Journal
that it would be a tragedy
for him not to rebuild.
- [Silverstein] It came down,
I think a day or two later.
And it was-- God,
it was awful. It was awful.
I mean, you couldn't describe it.
And there were firemen all over the site,
trying to find comrades,
policemen trying to find--
I mean, it was excruciating.
- [Philip] One of the things people forget
about the event and the re-development
is this little special period of time,
between the Tuesday of the attack
and the Friday when
George Bush came to town.
There is a sense, I think, among,
you know, I don't think I was alone
in feeling of that it was
an open narrative.
- [George Bush] I want you all to know--
you can't go any louder.
[people laugh]
- [Philip] Then Bush came to town on Friday
the 14th and he was touring site
and someone, he was speaking to
the hard hats
who are cleaning the place up,
standing on this pile of God knows what,
and someone said, "I can't hear you."
And he said, fairly famously,
- [Bush] "I can hear you."
[everybody laughs and cheers]
"I can hear you. The rest of the world
hears you and the people--
[cheering continues]
and the people who knocked these
buildings down, will hear all of us soon.
[all cheer]
- [Philip] As this was an attack on
our freedom narrative, came into being,
pressure on the site,
in addition to all the other things
that go into a construction site,
the pressure on the site became,
"This is our response
and it has to be defined."
In a context, where it's already
very difficult to do anything,
the site was being asked
to do the impossible.
No commercial office building
that I know of,
in the history of offices
and commerce, has ever been asked
to also be a symbol of defiant renewal
or a symbol of vengeance,
or a symbol of healing, you know.
That's just not what skyscrapers do.
All of a sudden, there's this idea
that this building is somehow going to
do something architectural, that will
magically make everyone feel better.
- [Mayor Giuliani] I really believe we
shouldn't think about this site out there,
right behind us, right here,
as a site for economic development.
and we should think about
a soaring monumental, beautiful memorial.
This could be a place
that gets remembered
a hundred and a thousand
years from now.
Like the great battlefields of Europe
and of the United States.
We have to be able to create something
here that enshrines this forever.
[crowd applauding]
- [Raab] When Mayor Guiliani gave
his farewell address, he suggested
that nothing should be rebuilt here,
that it'd simply become a memorial.
A large, serene memorial
to the people who died on 9/11.
There was never any chance of that
happening. I think the Mayor knew it.
I think the proof that he knew it
was to create the LMDC,
the Lower Manhattan Development
Corporation, in order to pass that
along to George Pataki, for fear that
a mayor, who was not a Republican,
was going to succeed Guiliani.
ALBANY
- [George Pataki] The LMDC was
right after September 11th.
Mayor Guiliani and I sat down and said,
"We're gonna need massive assistance.
We're gonna have help from Washington.
We're gonna have insurance proceeds.
And we need a vehicle, whose sole purpose,
so they won't get distracted, will be
to make sure that the funds
are appropriately targeted.
- [Reporter] The Governor of New York
is central to what eventually happens
in Lower Manhattan. Here's why.
Two agencies, the Lower Manhattan
Development Corporation and
the Port Authority control the process
and New York's Governor
controls half of each.
- [Philip] There's no single person
involved with the re-development
who had his much sway
on it as George Pataki.
He achieved that position
by creating the LMDC
and initially packing it with his cronies
and using it as almost like, control rods
to change the pace of the process.
At some point, he would slow it down,
at some point, he would speed it up,
purely to suit his needs
at any given point,
which were profound,
because he was running
for re-election during the process.
- [Reporter] Here in our area,
a jury will begin deliberating
over how much money will be available
to rebuild the World Trade Center Complex.
Developer Larry Silverstein is suing
several insurance companies claiming,
the attack on Twin Towers
was two separate events.
The insurers say it was one.
Billions of dollars are at stake
on the outcome.
- [Silverstein] First issue. One event,
two events. We needed, as it turns out,
we needed two events,
because to rebuild the Trade Center,
the cost to rebuild the Trade Center
would require, not just $3.5 billion,
it would require closer to $7 billion.
Right? We needed more money.
- [Roland Betts] I think
he was preoccupied with this
bizarre legal theory
that there were two buildings,
so therefore it was two separate incidents
and therefore,he had to double his return.
Most of us in the LMDC thought just
logically, that would be a silly result.
You know, you have insurance policy
on two buildings for a set number.
I don't see mathematically, how you're
gonna end up with more than a set number.
- [Janno Lieber] People argued about it
a little bit, like it was common sense,
but believe me, anyone who has read
an insurance policy knows
it's not a common sense industry,
it's all about the specific language
and what it means. And in fairness, that
was essential to protect the possibility
of rebuilding, that somebody talked about,
"How are we gonna get
the money to do this?"
The result was that Larry was a typecast,
I think, early on in the process,
as somebody who was fighting about money,
while people were worrying about
human loss and then about whether we
were gonna build something great.
And Larry was off fighting about money.
- [Silverstein] They did everything
they possibly could to excoriate,
to criticize, to denigrate.
It was just a constant flow.
Talk about, needing a thick skin
for that, let me tell you,
I just had to get thick fast.
Born in Brooklyn, it was not
a very pretty part of Brooklyn.
So, probably not one of the best,
probably one of the worst.
I remember we lived at the top of a--
either a six or a seven story walk-up.
It had the best view,
but you had to walk up.
It was not a very luxurious existence.
My parents, obviously, were struggling.
And then after that, I went to NYU.
And by this time, my father gravitated
into the real estate business.
He became a real estate broker.
He read someplace that real estate
was a foundation of wealth,
so he decided to become a broker.
I said, "The guys who make the money
are the guys who own the buildings."
I said, "We could become an owner."
I remember finding a building
down on East 23rd street,
so I remember finding how much it was.
Six-hundred thousand
it was for the building.
Six-hundred thousand, where do you get $600,000?
So what we did, we went to the people
my father had successfully leased
stores and lofts to. And then,
I had made the pitch.
They only joined us for a
small investment in the building.
And one after one another,
finally said, "yes."
And we bought buildings, bought larger buildings and we renovated buildings,
we altered them, we modernized them.
And then, ultimately, it led to finally
being the foundation. Pour in the slab
and building the building.
- [Lieber] 7 World Trade Center
was developed in the early 1980s,
because the Port Authority
had a piece of land,
just north of the World Trade Center site
and they decided to develop it.
And Silverstein won the bid.
And so, all of a sudden,
Silverstein was at a new level.
- [Silverstein] I remember
at the topping out ceremony of 7,
looking up at the Twin Towers,
and saying to myself,
"God, look at this."
But my building's big.
It's a 2 million foot building.
It's a big building.
But, look at that stuff, huge.
And there are two of them, right? Massive.
I said, "Wouldn't it be fantastic
if someday I'll own those?"
Got it done. Hence, therein started
the odyssey, six weeks before 9/11.
- [speaker] I think the Tower
should be built back.
I think it should be built tall,
as tall, if not taller.
I like to comment earlier about a
library. I always said I wanted a school.
- [speaker] You could also have
an exhibition hall.
You could have a concert hall.
There's enough room there.
- [speaker] How could you build
on sacred grounds?
The whole site should be a memorial.
- [speaker] Our new World Trade Center
Towers must be at least 111 storeys tall.
[crowd applause and cheers]
- [Lieber] People are starting to think
about what's going to be created there.
And ultimately, there's a debate
about what should happen
at the World Trade Center site,
which is classic New York,
with everybody taking very strong opinions
that pull in totally opposite directions,
where a lot of different people are
fighting for the one thing that they want.
What ought to be rebuilt there?
How do we respond to 9/11?
- [Rosaleen Tallon] I should call Sally
and tell them I'm two minutes away.
Excuse me. Sorry.
See, if you get behind
these slow people, you know.
- How are you doing, Rosaleen?
- Good to see you. Hi, Dorman.
[people chattering]
Good morning.
My name is Rosaleen Tallon.
This is my mother, Eileen.
We lost my brother, Sean Patrick Tallon.
He was a probationary firefighter
at Ladder 10, which is the firehouse
at the World Trade Center.
If you look at Oklahoma City,
those families are really an integral
part of the process to
decision-making process.
So, to say at a minimum,
that's what we're asking.
Include us in the process.
Because to this point,
we have not been included.
[dog barking in distant]
[kids playing in distant]
We knew he was always going to be
either a policeman or fireman.
It was just, you know,
as they say,"It's in the Irish."
The first tower collapsed.
And then, we arrived home
and we watched the tower on TV
and we knew that Sean was up there
because his company
would've been first on the scene.
So, there was no doubt in our minds
that he was in there.
I remember standing at the precipice,
right outside the firehouse door.
These people are buried inside there.
I mean, loved ones. I mean,
knowing Sean was in there,
I mean, my God,
like looking at that pile,
and knowing that my little brother
was in there
and there wasn't anything
I could do about it.
Because of the enormity of what happened
and all of these people died in there,
my parents were definitely hoping
that the site could, say,
be a green field of remembrance.
But we realized that wasn't going to be.
There were too many commercial
and real estate interests that
you know, they had to build back up
their square footage.
- [Pataki] One of the things
that people don't appreciate is that
there was an enormous economic fallout
after September 11th.
We lost a 100,000 private sector jobs
that morning.
We lost millions of square feet
of office space.
Companies were leaving New York,
so it had to get built.
And the initial plan was,
let the Port Authority do it.
THE PORT AUTHORITY
- [Kenneth Ringler] I was having dinner
at a local pub around the corner
from my apartment and somebody was
sitting next to me and they said,
"So, what do you do?" and I said,
"Well, I run the Port Authority."
And they said, "Does that mean you
do the bus scheduling?"
And I had to explain that
the Port Authority
was a little more
than the bus terminal.
- [Lieber] Port Authority built
the Lincoln Tunnel
and George Washington Bridge
and many of our biggest
transportation facilities
and also built the World Trade Center.
- [Silverstein] I obligated myself to pay
the ground rent of $120 million a year
to the Port Authority for 99 years,
which is like in perpetuity with
no abatements of any kind
'cause no one anticipated the 9/11 event.
- [Kenneth] You know, it stuck in his
craw that he had to do that.
But, the fact of the matter is,
he was insured to do that.
It's called business
interruption insurance.
And you continue paying your rent.
- [Raab] Here is Larry Silverstein paying,
I think, $10 million a month
ground rent at nothing.
- [Reporter] The plans are moving ahead
to rebuild one of the buildings
destroyed in the
World Trade Center attacks.
7 World Trade Center collapsed
several hours after the Twin Towers fell.
The owner of the 47-storey building
hopes to break ground on a new structure
on September 11th.
- [Silverstein] So, once we started
designing the building,
people came out of the woodwork and said,
"Silverstein, you're crazy.
No one's gonna come back down.
I mean, this is foolhardy. Second of all,
you got that burning mass
immediately to the South area,
it's ground zero. It's a mess.
I mean, how is anybody gonna
come back around? It's foolishness.
I mean, you're really doing yourself
irreparable harm."
- [Lieber] 7 World trade Center,
we wereable to get the building going
very quickly, because it was
just us and the Port Authority
and that was it.
We didn't have to deal with
a ton of different government agencies.
Across the street was totally different.
On the city side, we had the Mayor,
the Economic Development Corporation,
the Industrial Development Agency,
the Department
of Environmental Protection,
the Department of Transportation,
Department of Design and Construction,
the Police Department,
the Fire Department,
the Buildings Department,
the City Council and
the Local Community Board.
On the State level, we had
the Empire State Development Corporation,
the Department
of Environmental Conservation,
the State Historic Preservation Office,
the New York State Department
of Transportation,
the New York State Office
of Emergency Management,
and then, even at the Federal level,
we had Congress,
we had the White House,
Department of Housing
and Urban Development
the Federal Department
of Homeland Security,
FEMA, SBA, EDA, OSHA,
and not to forget
the Army Corps of Engineers,
so it just went on and on and on.
- [Betts] I started calling meetings
of the heads of all the agencies
and Silverstein's is on. And the meetings
had 50, 60 people in the room.
It was completely unworkable.
Tremendous cross currents.
Silverstein and the Port Authority
wanted a 10 million square feet of
office space and at the other end,
some victim families wanted this
to be hollowed ground.
They wanted nothing.
There was another group
that said that they wanted to see the
Twin Towers rebuilt exactly
as the Twin Towers.
From the beginning,
I was pretty pessimistic
that this could actually be coralled.
- [Raab] Once the site was cleaned up,
people expected something to arise
magically from the dust. Hey,
it's New York City,
let's get it done yesterday.
But I don't think people
get the complexity of the site
especially below grade and the fact
that it's literally a couple hundred feet
from a big river and that it ain't easy
to keep that river from pushing
through the earth on this site.
And in fact, that was one of the
most daunting, if not the most daunting
challenge of the original building,
the original Twin Towers was,
how do you keep the Hudson River out?
- [Announcer] The site actually consisted
of water log landfill,
which had accumulated over two centuries
out of old wharves and debris.
To support the great weight of the towers,
foundations had had to be dug
down 70 feet to bedrock.
An underground wall was built
completely sealing the site.
Excavation began.
- [Pataki] Given the ownership,
given the emotion,
given that the technical
engineering challenges,
you couldn't have a more difficult site.
But everybody knew that.
And it's what you have.
- [Betts] What we decided to do was,
engage a firm called, Beyer Blinder Belle.
And so, Beyer Blinder Belle came in
and they became the architects of record.
- [Philip] They were hired by the LMDC
to just crunch the numbers
and show what could happen spatially
in that place, using these numbers
dictated by Larry Silverstein's lease.
With this big pile of square footage
and this kinda little area,
what are we gonna doand what's possible?
So, Beyer Blinder Belle was working
on these designs and the public
desire for a meaningful, symbolic
architectural solution reserved
building through the months and they
happen to converge in public
in the Javits Center, in this
very hi-tech, super managed,
so-called 21st century town meeting.
- [Reporter] Six proposals are on
the table. Today, 5000 New Yorkers
will have a chance to voice
their opinions about those plans
at a meeting called, Listening to the City.
[people chattering]
- [speaker] The footprints is not to
sort of acknowledge some great
architecture, but the place is
sort of charged with meaning
and so many loved ones in layers,
that it is one way to have a somber,
yet, not offensive memorial.
- [speaker] I just wanna see as much left
that was there before September 11th,
still there after this
scariest memory constructed.
- [Betts] And everybody could participate.
They had little computer boards there.
Everybody could vote for anything.
And everybody could talk and so on.
- [speaker] Sometimes, when you look
at all of this, you wonder,
"Where's the memorial?"
Have we just moved on and
created tax-free shopping days?
- [speaker] We don't like the fact
that green as an isolated rectangle
with buildings around it.
- Not enough green.
- Go back to this drawing book.
- Strongly, this is strongly helpful.
- Get new architects.
- [Betts] And the comments in real time,
would show up on a screen
'cause the typing
would show right up there.
And then people would vote
for what they like and didn't like.
And somewhere about two-thirds the way
through the meeting,
a comment showed up on the screen saying,
"I hate all these plans.
They look like Albany."
Okay, and I really think
that captured the day
because I think everybody looked as if,
"Yeah, they kinda do."
- [Pataki] It was a perfectly good plan
for a site that didn't have
the emotional and historic
importance to America.
But from that sense, it was unacceptable.
So at that point, we said no.
- [Philip] After the Beyer Blinder Belle
plans were essentially shut down,
you know, publicly, at the Javits Center,
the Pataki messaging machine
was in a little bit of a crisis
because the election was approaching
and the idea that he "wasn't doing
enough at Ground Zero fast enough."
had already been injected
into the campaign.
And then, there was a moment of the LMDC
sort of casting around, saying,
"What now?"
- [Betts] I called an emergency meeting
of the LMDC and I said,
"Look, we gotta scrap this thing.
This is nowhere. These plans stink.
Everybody knows they stink.
And we gotta do something."
"Okay, well what do you wanna do?"
I said, "I wanna have an architectural
competition. A true competition."
- [Pataki] We are going to go out
and have a process
and engage some of the
world's greatest architects.
- [Philip] And the next step
was to seek out the visionaries.
- [Announcer] The LMDC is now looking
for new international design teams
to come up with still more concepts
using broad guidelines that include,
a tall symbol or structure
seen in the skyline,
the footprints of the original Twin Towers
would remain undeveloped.
- [Philip] By the following December,
every network in the world,
set up to film this dramatic unveiling
of the new future of Ground Zero.
- [Betts] We're about to see
seven very different visions
by some extraordinary thinkers
in their approach to the restoration
of hope and optimism to Lower Manhattan.
- [Architect] We tried to make with
these united towers,
what we call, "The City in the Sky,"
which at the 60th floor.
These towers come together and join.
- [Architect] The two tall towers in
the middle are at least 1400 feet tall.
They symbolize triumph.
They're sort of universal.
They're standing there on big shoulders
with their hands in the air.
- [Architect] A natural fact.
It's two towers, which kiss
and touch and become one.
- [Daniel Libeskind] When I first started
on the competition, everybody had an idea.
Every New Yorker, every member
of the family, every uncle, aunt, niece,
nephew, every acquaintance.
When they found out that I was doing it,
"I have an idea. Do this, do this."
And it suddenly occurred to me
that this was really not just
an architectural issue,
it was an issue of the soul of people,
because everyone was somehow,
part of that day.
- [Betts] We had a broad spectrum,
but it was clear that there
were two that emerged.
One was Daniel Libeskind
and one was Rafael Viñoly.
- [Rafael Viñoly] We started
this process, essentially by defining
for ourselves a principle, what we felt
was moral obligation,
which was not only to remember
the ones that perished in this tragedy,
but also, to use their memory
to elevate our memory
to become the inspiration
for a better future.
- [Betts] The Viñoly plan was
very, very different.
The Viñoly plan had these round cylinders,
if you will, that you could see through.
The idea was that they were preserving
as a hollowed ground
the space in which people died.
Well, this was spunky.
This was really different
and really interesting.
- [Viñoly] The skyland of Manhattanis
re-structured, re-constructed
with the icons of the public life.Thanks.
[crowd applause]
- [Betts] I'm now happy
to present Daniel Libeskind.
[applause]
- [Libeskind] Thanks.Thank you very much.
I arrived by ship to New York
as a teenager, an immigrant.
and like millions of others before me,
my first sight was that of the
Statue of LIberty and the
amazing skyline of Manhattan.
I have never forgotten that sight
or what it actually stands for.
This is what this project is all about.
- [Philip] Everyone had been looking
for a leader or you know,
someone to put a non-political,
non-bureaucratic face in the process
and all of a sudden, arrives this guy
with the perfect back story
and you know, the ability to present
it, you know, super effectively.
- [Libeskind] I grew up in Poland.
Then to America, where my father had
his only surviving sisters who
were an Al Fritz, from a family
of ten brothers and sisters, so he was
determined to come to New York.
It represented everything that people
dreamed about and it still does.
Those who are lost have become heroes.
To commemorate those lost lives,
I created two large public spaces.
The park of heroes and the wedge of light.
The sky will become home again to
a towering spire 1776 feet tall,
creating an icon that speaks to our
vitality in the face of danger
and our optimism in the
aftermath of tragedy.
- [Philip] When asked to do this thing,
which is so impossible
that it's almost magic, you know,
architects can fill in the difference
by attaching words to the project.
People understand words.
And Libeskind's architecture always
comes heavily loaded with words.
And the design he presented at Ground Zero
with the matrix of heroes
and the wedge of light and the tower
that through a tight, somehow spoke
about the Declaration of Independence.
All of that stuff bridges the gap between
what can be, you know,
very funny looking architecture and things
that real people can actually understand,
because "I'm gonna make you feel better
about September 11th,"
is not a thing
that a building can say.
- [Libeskind] It's 1776 feet high,
very important and it is not just about
nations, it's about ecological zones,
ecological regions.
The twenty upper storeys will be
developed into very spectacular--
it's like a park standing vertically
and of course--
- [Philip] Daniel Libeskind read
the political landscape perfectly
and pitched to the city in the world
and the powers that be, kind of merging
of you know, a hip architecture
that was also flag-waving.
[crowd applause]
- [Betts] I was so engaged in it.
I thought it was phenomenal.
But I didn't know
what other people would think.
So, I went home that night
and I started looking at newspapers
and I looked around tomorrow
morning's papers.
I looked, there's a site where you
can find every newspaper in the world.
And I must've looked at 300 that night.
I did it almost all night just looking.
I just can't believe it. I tell my wife,
"Look at this, God."
You know, in the middle of nowhere,
Malaysia... and here it is.
One or more of those images
was on the front page
of every newspaper in the world.
And I think that wasn't lost
on Viñoly and Libeskind
and somebody was gonna win and therefore,
the stakes were unbelievably high
and they wanted to win.
So, it did get a little naughty.
- [Philip] After Libeskind and THINK were
sort of selected as finalist,
there was, you know,
campaigns of muttering.
- [Libeskind] You know, everybody wants
to win and you know, if you're naive,
you don't know what kind of forces
are arrayed against you.
There was not a minute
that it was just, "Go, relax."
You know, meditate. It was a constant
passionate sort of struggle.
- [Philip] And the kind of things,
you know, that sort of rovey
on political tactics,
taken into the world of architecture
and being propagated by amateurs.
So it was a good time for all.
- [Lieber] It was blood sport and these
guys were going for the biggest prize
the architecture had ever seen.
And there's a lot at stake for that.
- [Philip] Libeskind had chosen to leave
the pit empty, preserved as a memorial,
so his opponents started whispering
that it was a pit of death
and an open grave and kind of,
you know, there's a lot of ways
to see how that gesture
could be perceived as inappropriate.
And then, the THINK team went
you know, very high up in the air
with these open steel--
kind of Eiffel towers, so the Libeskinds
started saying that they were
skeletons in the sky.
- [Betts] So, we finally came to the
point of determining who we wanted to win
and we chose Viñoly's plan.
- [Libeskind] It was early in the morning.
I remember being in a car,
taxi in New York, going somewhere
Lower Manhattan and the headline,
the day before the competition
was to be judged in the New York Times
was "Scheme selected, scheme ex-selected."
Was that my scheme?
And of course, when I read that headline,
I was crushed.
- [Pataki] I remember waking up
in the morning seeing the front page
of the Times that the LMDC is going
to choose the Viñoly plan and going,
"No, this can't be."
Because I thought, the Viñoly plan,
one was, unbuildable, two was,
economically unsound and three,
were the footprints where had these
skeletons really rising into the sky
that to me symbolize
the destruction of the past,
instead of the hope of the future.
And I just thought it was a terrible idea.
- [Betts] He just ripped Viñoly's plan.
And he said it looks like these oil tanks
in New Jersey and no one's ever
gonna want to walk in there,
or they're gonna fall down,
just all this stuff.
So now, we were in a pretty awful position
here because the LMDC had voted,
not just as a site committee,
but as the full LMDC
and expressed a clear preference
for Viñoly and basically,
Pataki came in and kinda just pulled
the rug out from under the LMDC
and you know, he just
reversed the decision.
- [Pataki] How are you? Good to see you.
- [Libeskind] Great day.
This is a great day.
- [Betts] And so, in a sense,
the Libeskind plan became his plan.
- [Libeskind] It suddenly dawned on me
what immense responsibility I have.
It wasn't just all great. Oh my, God.
Now, with these few lines on paper,
how am I going to be able to do
what I promised to do?
- [Announcer] Out of this gaping wound
in of the heart of
the New York Financial Center, where
the 1300 foot tall Twin Towers once stood,
an even taller building will rise.
- [Pataki] The design plan
has an inspiring spire.
- [Libeskind] It is the biggest challenge.
The most profoundly moving
emotionally intellectual,
architecturally spiritual project
I've ever done here, of course.
- [Philip] For three months, Libeskind
gave Pataki everything he needed.
[Libeskind laughs]
He got in front of any camera
and told a gripping story
and there was imagery to attach to it.
[bell ringing]
And he was ringing
the right political bells
and everyone was happy.
Except for Larry Silverstein.
- [Lieber] Larry actually preferred
Libeskind's entry to the others.
But once it became clear that Libeskind
wanted to design the building,
in addition to being the master planner,
we did get into a little conflict with him
because Libeskind had done a couple
of buildings of moderate size,
some architecturally dramatic ones,
including the museum in Berlin.
But he had not done a skyscraper,
he had not done very tall tower,
which is a completely different exercise.
- [Betts] What Libeskind was picked for
was the master plan.
He was not picked to design and build
skyscrapers, something he had never done.
- [Lieber] So, as Larry Silverstein
explained to Libeskind once when
we were having a meeting, he said,
"Dan, if I'm gonna have open heart
surgery, I wanna have somebody
who's done it before.
And a building of 1700 feet in height,
is the architectural equivalent
of open heart surgery."
And Dan's wife, who is his partner,
you know, in his practice said,
"He's a quick learner," and Larry said,
"Not on my heart, you're not gonna learn
how to do open heart surgery."
- [Silverstein] This meeting's over.
We're done.
She says, "Don't get excited."
I said, "I'm not excited," I said,
"Just wanna say this meeting's over.
I'm having no further discussion
about the redesign.
It's off the table. Finished.
- [Libeskind] Here's a man with money,
with power, with the idea that
it belongs to him, he had his own ideas
with his own architects.
- [David Childs] Larry came to me
and he said, "Your trade in life,
what you're a specialist is,
is tall office buildings.
I need you to do this."
- [Lieber] Larry announced the truth,
which is he's gonna do the building
with the architect he chose,
which is David Childs,
from Skidmore, Owings and Merrill.
He did the Worldwide Plaza building,
he did the Bank
of New York Operations Center,
he's done a lot of big buildings.
- [Libeskind] David is a, you know,
very accomplished, very powerful
architect running a firm
of thousands of people.
You know, it was really kind of
David and Goliath. [laughs]
- [Childs] It was a functioning, operating
office building in a capitalistic society.
This was not just a piece of
sculpture there in the air.
Some time in the middle of the summer,
we were summoned to a meeting
at the offices of the LMDC
and there was a negotiation.
- [Philip] Libeskind and Childs were
literally thrown into a room together.
- [Childs] You've gotta have somebody
in charge. You can't have two generals.
You've gotta have one
that has 51% of the vote.
And so, that's what I insisted on.
[people chattering]
- [Libeskind] This is not a press
conference. This is a photo op.
- [reporter] Have you ever seen
happier faces in your life?
- [Silverstein] Once or twice.
- [Libeskind] It's a great day.
Fantastic collaboration.
Wait, we have to roll up our sleeves.
We gotta get to work.
- [Childs] If body language says anything,
this is the picture.
- [reporter] What's the reality?
- [Libeskind] It's real, it's real.
[cameras clicking]
- [Silverstein] Okay, let's go.
Thank you.
Right behind you.
Keep going, keep going.
- [Libeskind] David, they want us---
[Childs] This is our scheme,
see how well--
[Libeskind laughing]
- [Lieber] But it was very clear
from the beginning that these guys
did not look at things the same way.
Childs and his team would present,
you know, technical issues
and how they propose to solve
them or options for solving them
and Libeskind's comments tended
to be focused on more ethereal,
symbolic and general issues, you know.
I think Dan said,
"The top has to be more meaningful."
And that you could see
that Childs' blood rising.
- [Childs] I think that in fact, that
Libeskind thought that he would have
a more of a role than I was gonna be
somehow change and be willing to
just execute his role as a designer.
Frankly, Larry wouldn't permit that.
- [Libeskind] He's an industrialist.
He wants to make profits.
He has an empire, you know.
It's not the philanthropic enterprise,
it's how to create profits,
which I appreciate.
Now, what would New York be
if people were not entrepreneurial
to want make money. But that often came
into tension with other ideas.
- [Pataki] When our work is done,
the history of Lower Manhattan
would have been written,
not by the terrorists
who attacked our city,
but by the millions of New Yorkers,
who stood up to defend it.
By the 5th anniversary of the attack,
September 11th 2006,
we will top off a new icon.
The 1776-foot tall Freedom Tower.
[applause]
- [Raab] My vast--people
close to the governor,
was that political calculation
or a spur of the moment,
naming it, "The Freedom Tower."
And the best answer I've heard
is that it had been discussed,
but no one had really signed off on it
and no one was sure of it until it came
out of his mouth during the speech.
- [Pataki] What is 1776?
It's a symbol of our freedom.
It's the year we proclaimed
our independence.
So it just made sense that word just
kinda fell in and fit the building.
- [Philip] There's a letter in the New York Post that was brilliant.
The letter said, "This building is nothing
but a perch for George Pataki
to climb up and gaze off
in the direction of Washington."
And that was true. Pataki was
actively using the process to further
his political ambition
as any politician would.
- [Pataki] Good morning.
We're here today for the unveiling
of the model of the Freedom Tower.
When Daniel Libeskind revealed
his master site plan, the idea was
to create a building, the tallest
building in the world, yes,
but symbolically, 1776 feet tall.
But mostly today, is a celebration
of the successful collaboration
of two brilliant architects,
who understand that
this is not just a building,
this is a symbol of freedom.
So to Daniel Libeskind and to
David Childs, congratulations.
[cameras clicking]
[applause]
- That's it?
- That's it.
Don't trip now as we go on there.
[people chattering]
[cameras clicking]
[people chatting]
- [Philip] When Libeskind and Childs
allegedly started working together,
the kind of face saving design that came
out of that, had this big stick on top.
And that stick and the numbers
1776 were the only thing
that survived of the original
Libeskind concept.
They presented this huge model
that was 10 feet tall or something.
It lit from within and who knows
how much money was spent on it.
And as they were moving it
out of the Federal Hall,
where they had the presentation,
the S-1 guys broke the stick off,
so it could clear the door, you know.
And that was the last
we saw of Danny's stick.
- [Rosaleen] No matter what people talk about,
buildings or their real estate,
Ground Zero is ground zero
for what happened there.
So, the most important thing was
how we were gonna remember
what happened there to those people.
- [speaker] And this eternal flame
will be visible, just like the tower was,
so you don't have to come to this
memorial to remember what happened here.
- [speaker] The key feature of my design
is that every visitor
will clearly visualize and absorb
the enormity of the sacrifice.
Every victim will be represented
by his or her own individual
life-sized human statue.
- [speaker] We could then have
two or three foot crystal birds.
One for each life lost.
[applause]
- [Pataki] We wanted public involvement,
so we invited submissions.
We got thousands.
- [Anchorman] More than 5000 people
submitted proposals for a memorial
at the site of the World Trade Center.
Today, a committee chose this one.
It's called, Reflecting Absence.
Designed by New Yorker, Michael Arad,
it will include the names
of everyone killed in the 9/11 attacks
on the World Trade Center.
- [Michael Arad] I was working as
an assistant architect
for the New York City Housing
Authority, Design Department,
when I found out there was a competition
for the design of the memorial,
and I had to do this.
There's no sort of rational explanation
for why you get so drawn into it.
I came across this quarry in South Orange
and there's just something very beautiful
and evocative about it, because it had
this sort of clearly traced out absence
of all the rock
that had been excavated out,
but was softened by the water
and by the trees and I think that
helped me to start thinking about
the Memorial Plaza.
Days after the attack, I remember
biking around Lower Manhattan
at night and I made my way
to Washington Square Park
and I found myself standing
near that central fountain,
the grand fountain.
People placed candles there.
And I felt like I was part of that group.
You know, I came there,
not knowing anybody
and not a word was said.
And I left a few minutes later
without having said anything
to anybody
but, I left completely changed.
All of a sudden,
that notion of sort of being
cruelly removed from the life of the city,
I mean, that just shattered. And we're part of it, a greater all.
You had to be.
[cycling sound]
- [Rosaleen] Our neighborhood here
in Yonkers is full of police officers
and fire fighters. So, after 9/11,
I met other family members
and they were very, very intent
on making sure that,
as they said, the brothers
were listed with their ranks,
and I thought that was a no-brainer.
So, they asked me, would I care
to join the group, advocating for 9/11
issues, and they seemed like such
a simple thing to become involved in.
- [Betts] I mean, simple things like,
what's the order of the names?
Is it organized alphabetically
by last name?
Is it organized alphabetically by last name
within the firemen's group?
Are the firemen over here
and the police over here?
I mean, these are things
that were debated for years.
- [Lieber] The Mayor started seeing
the Memorial was not coming together
as quickly or as well
as everybody had hoped.
And he took ownership of it.
He literally stepped up,
became the Chairman of the Board,
raised the money and started
to push the construction
schedules through.
- [Rosaleen] Mayor Bloomberg,
it's his way or the highway.
That's what I have felt.
He's a man that cast us aside
and made us seem like
we couldn't get over our grief.
CITY HALL
- [Michael Bloomberg] People's views
change with time.
There's an emotion that, as soon as
you lose a loved one,
that it's very different than
an emotion that you have
five and ten and twenty years later.
And we have to make sure we don't
respond to the first and in fact,
have a better perspective.
That's not to say,
that you treat people cavalierly
or don't listen to them.
- [Rosaleen] The Mayor and the LMDC,
they were able to say,
"Oh, look at these families."
They're constantly complaining.
And then, when other issues came up,
"Oh, look, here comes the families again.
They're slowing the process down."
They actually blamed us
for slowing Ground Zero down.
- [Betts] And so, they actually stopped
bugging the Mayor.
But they went to Pataki and they found
a very receptive ear in Pataki.
- [Pataki] We always try to include
family members every step of the way,
as decisions were made and listen
to them and when you have,
obviously, thousands and thousands
of family members,
you're never going to have unanimity,
you're going to have divergent opinions.
- [Philip] Just when the effects
of the Governors' race were winding down,
the Republicans announced that
in 2004, they'd be hosting
the Republican Convention.
You know, in Midtown, but within
kind of easy commute from Ground Zero.
And it was clear that Pataki couldn't allow
Ground Zero to be a festering mess
of selfish infighting, as it had become.
We need to show some progress.
- [Pataki] On July 4th, as fireworks
burst in the sky,
ephemeral reminders of our liberty,
we will begin to reclaim
our skyline with a permanent
symbol of our freedom.
On July 4th 2004, we will break ground
on the Freedom Tower.
[applause]
- [Lieber] The Governor was in haste
to plant his footprint at Ground Zero.
And he had a beautiful cornerstone
with quite a moving inscription on it
to be planted at a spot where
the Freedom Tower was going to rise.
- [Philip] First of all, towers
don't have cornerstones,
but if you wanna lay a
symbolic cornerstone, that's nice.
- [Betts] I remember it.
I think it was a media event,
it wasn't a construction event.
♪ [music] ♪
♪ [marching band playing] ♪
- [Choir] ♪ For the land of the free,
and the home of the brave ♪
[crowd applause]
- [Pataki] Today is the 4th of July,
Independence day.
Today, we lay the cornerstone
for a new symbol of the city
and of this country,
and of our resolve to triumph
in the face of terror.
Today, we build the Freedom Tower.
[applause]
- [Lieber] Of all these things,
the choreography is charged.
Politicians want to be seen in photos,
certain kinds of settings,
who's in the picture, who's not
in the picture has political ramifications.
And I guess, the vision that the State
people had was, in the end,
the politicians would be in
the big shot that would end up
on the front page of papers and they
didn't really want Larry in the shot.
[choir singing]
A lot of the politicians
were uncomfortable with having somebody
who was a business person
in the middle of this.
But Larry, when they walked over
to the cornerstone and inspected it,
Larry went with the flow.
♪ [choir singing on background] ♪
[applause]
And after it's over, I'm walking out.
And one or two of the Pataki aides,
button hole me
and begin to really let me have it,
yelling at me, you know,
in full view of my wife, about how
Larry had ruined the shot because
he didn't follow the choreography
and he went with the group
when he was supposed to,
I guess,magically disappear.
But it just was a reminder at the time
that they had mixed feelings
about private developers
being part of the story,
and about this private developer
being part of the story of the rebuilding,
even though, we were the ones
who were building the buildings.
[applause]
- [Pataki] We were ready
to go with the Freedom Tower.
The tallest building
ever built in America,
and the symbol of our freedom
and it was all set.
- [Lieber] But the one thing that
nobody knew was that the Port Authority
and the Police Department
had not communicated well,
about issues concerning security
features in that building.
- [Raab] Because that base, that exposed
base of the Freedom Tower design
at that point, was considered by the
NYPD to be a severe terrorist risk
and where the building was placed,
which was quite close
to the highway was also
perceived by the NYPD to be placing
the building at risk of a car bombing.
So, the building was gonna have
to be moved, therefore making
the cornerstone laying
absolutely pointless.
When that communication started
with the Port Authority as a matter
of first controversy and then burial.
Apparently, there were claims
that yes, the NYPD sent a letter,
but it got lost.
- [Silverstein] How can this be,
in this modern era, this day and age,
with communication over this,
how could this possibly happen?
The complete lack of coordination
between the two.
- [Ringler] If the letter was
such a big deal,
if I was on the other end of that letter
and didn't get a response,
I probably would've gotten a phone call
saying, "Did you get my letter?"
- [Lieber] And the whole project
just stopped that.
- [Reporter] Mr. Mayor,
with regard to the Freedom Towers,
why are security concerned
just now being presented?
- [Bloomberg] Well, they're not just
now being, you couldn't be more wrong.
The security concerns
have been there since 1993.
1993, there was a bombing
at the World Trade Center
and we did not learn our lesson.
This is a building, particularly,
Freedom Tower,
that is built to be a symbol.
And we are not going to rush
in to doing anything that doesn't
take into account the security measures
that the Police Department
and plenty of other people
think are appropriate.
- [Lieber] It's impossible to describe
the frustration that we all felt.
In fact, we had to go back
and come up with a new building.
- [Silverstein] I was crushed by it,
literally crushed.
I felt it was terribly unfair
and a tragic waste of time,
effort, energy and money,
that was needed for the purpose
of rebuilding the World Trade Center.
- [Childs] That changed
the game, entirely.
Because we couldn't modify the building.
We couldn't move it onto another site,
so we were in effect by that decision
given a clean slate of
clean sheet of paper to work on.
- [Lieber] The building moved
to the east away from the road.
And then, we came up
with a completely new design.
- [Anchorman] New York officials today
unveil the latest redesign
of the Freedom Tower to be built
in Ground Zero with the reinforced
concrete base for bomb protection.
The tower will be 1776 feet tall,
its proportions and external skin
recalling the lost Twin Towers.
- [Ringler] I could remember
shuttling back and forth
between Daniel and David,
trying to get Daniel to say
that this is a beautiful building
and you know, and he kept looking in.
Finally, he said,
"Yeah, I think I like it.
I think I like it."
So, I said, I called up
Governor's office and said,
"Dan is gonna say nice things. I think
we're not gonna have an issue here."
- [Libeskind] The tower that we have now,
after all the efforts,
is even a better tower
than we have before.
It is a slender tower,
it's an elegant tower,
it's a tower that rises
in a crystal-like form--
- [Betts] Daniel Libeskind was part
of that in name only.
He had absolutely nothing to do with
what we now know as the Freedom Tower.
All that's left of Libeskind's influence
is the height of the building.
[cameras clicking]
- [Lieber] The new design was rolled out
without people criticizing it
and we were back in business,
and in fact, building.
- [Anchorman] Well, today our Federal Jury
decided that for insurance purposes,
the destruction of the World Trade Center
was two separate events, not one,
as insurance companies were hoping for.
And this means the lease holder,
Larry Silverstein can collect twice
from some companies because
separate planes hit the two towers.
This decision is the latest twist
to Silverstein's effort to turn his
$3.5 billion insurance policy
on the Trade Center Complex,
into a $7 billion payout.
- [Lieber] And in the end, we ended up
recovering the equivalent of about
one and a half,
$4.5 billion dollars of insurance.
And mind you, that $4.5 billion
sounds like a lot of money,
but it's not enough money to rebuild
the office space that was destroyed.
- [Ringer] It was decided
to approach him and say,
"Can we re-negotiate the deal and
perhaps, lessen your rental obligations,
and return some of the sites
to the Port Authority
who would then go on
and develop them."
- [Anchorwoman] A deal must be reached
today between World Trade Center
lease holder Larry Silverstein
and the Port Authority
which owns the land
on what to do with the site
beyond the Memorial.
Governor Pataki set
the March 14th deadline last year,
in an effort to get
the rebuilding ball rolling.
- [Lieber] We gave them proposal after
proposal, we couldn't get any response.
And they left everything to,
literally, the last two days.
- [Ringler] We got to the
day of the deadline
and our teams were working
all day at our offices.
And I was there. I was going from room
to room and we were progressing.
We broke for dinner and hoped
everybody would be back
by 7:00 or so, and we were gonna
continue the discussions
and hopefully consummate a deal.
And I ordered pizza out for our folks
and we sat around the
conference table eating pizza.
As I read later, Larry
and his team were so ecstatic,
they ordered from a French restaurant
and had a party.
And they didn't come back.
We kept calling, asking,"Where are you?"
"We're meeting with our key people.
We'll be there. We'll be there."
- [Lieber] And we came back and it was
about 9:00 or so, 9:00 to 9:30.
Larry Silverstein sat down,
drank two cups of coffee
'cause he thought we were gonna
be there for a long time.
- [Ringler] And I think he and his team,
again, it's only my perception,
felt that because there was a deadline
and that we wanted to honor
the Governor's wishes, that perhaps there
was more nickels on the table for him.
I walked down the hall and Larry
and his team were sitting at the table.
Everybody's sitting around there, smiling.
And I think I felt like an ancient Roman
going into the Colosseum with the lions.
- [Lieber] Ken Ringler came into that
conference room, where we were sitting.
And in very blue language, told us
to get the "F" outta his office,
to pay our "effing" rent, and you know,
we were a bunch of bums
and they were coming after us.
- [Silverstein] All I remember
was being surprised as hell.
Because we genuinely were there
for the purpose of making a deal
with the Port that night, clearly.
And it made no sense to me,
literally made no sense.
And then of course, the next day,
diffused a lot.
- [Ringler] We thought we were moving
in the right direction.
Then at 11:35 was it, Sir?
- [speaker] 11:35.
11:35, they came back with a proposal,
where their demands
were just as high as they were before,
they're increasing their demands,
and quite honestly, in my view,
I think they thought they had leverage
that we were going to back down
because we wanted to get a deal
and we wanted to move
the Freedom Tower forward.
We're not going to make short-sight
a deal with Larry Silverstein.
- [Silverstein] Negotiation with
the Port collapsed.
Next thing I know, New York Times,
"Governor to Larry Silverstein:
Stand Aside.
You're obstructing progress at the site."
Oh, my God.
- [Ringler] Larry was losing
the public battle.
And within days, there was a
New York Times editorial,
the political leaders galvanized
around it and said,
"No. Enough is enough."
We decided to put an agreement together
and bring it back to Larry
and basically, not say take it
or leave it, but as I told Larry
when I brought it up to him,
"It's this close to take it or leave it
as we're gonna get."
- [Chuck Scarborough] Good evening.
An agreement between World Trade Center
developer Larry Silverstein
and the Port Authority, means
construction on the Freedom Tower
could finally begin.
Perhaps, by week's end.
- [Sue Simmons] The deal will give
Port Authority control
of the long-delayed Freedom Tower,
but reward Silverstein with three
other prime developing sites along
the eastern side of Ground Zero.
- [Silverstein] That was when
we relinquished control of
The Freedom Tower and Tower 5
and kept Towers 2, 3 and 4.
Did we think it was fair? Not necessarily.
But the important thing was
to keep the momentum going.
- [Lieber] What we got out of the deal
was a commitment by the Port Authority
that they would dig the hole
on the east side of the site.
The 80-foot hole and put
in the infrastructure and fully prepare
those sites for construction.
- [Jon Stewart] If you remember,
New York City was attacked
four and a half years ago
and since that time,
we have been locked in a vicious
battle over construction of the
tallest, shiniest, terrorist,
tauntiest skyscraper in the world.
[audience laughing]
The 1776 foot tall Freedom Tower!
- [Pataki] Today, we lay the cornerstone
for a new symbol of the city
and of this country,
and of our resolve
to triumph in the face of terror.
- [Stewart] So that was the site
two years ago.
And today...Oh!
[audience laughing]
[cameras clicking]
- [speaker] Governor, good morning.
- [Pataki] Good morning.
Good morning.
This is a great day for New York
and a great day for America.
Today, we begin construction
on the Freedom Tower,the final element--
- [Betts] When the press would start
ranting and raving about no progress,
there'd be a ceremony.
I never went to any of them.
[excavator engine running]
[applause]
- [Raab] The cornerstone had to come out
because the Freedom Tower
had to be redesigned.
The cornerstone had been
sitting in a plywood box.
They're taking this thing out,
not literally under the cover of night,
but goddamn close to the cover of night.
No one is supposed to know that
they're pulling the--
it's too much of an embarrassment
to let anyone in the media know
that this is going to happen.
- [Reporter] What became
of the cornerstone itself?
- [Pataki] I honestly don't know,
but to me, I thought it would be nice
to have it in the lobby of the actual
Freedom Tower that's constructed.
I haven't had a chance to
talk to David Childs about it.
- [Raab] My joke was always driving
to Pataki's house.
You know, and put it down his front lawn.
Ring the doorbell and drive away
as fast as you can.
[laughs]
[crowd applauding and cheering]
- [speaker] One , two, done. [crowd cheering]
- [Raab] One of the ironies is
during the middle of all the drama
back in the spring of '06,
we opened 7 World Trade Center.
- [Betts] That's the best thing Larry did,
was he went in.
He just plowed ahead,
rebuilt World Trade Center number 7.
I think that was important for the public
to see construction and to see action
down there and to see something
coming out of the ground.
- [Lieber] It saw a finished product.
It saw something that was high-style
that was green and that gave confidence
that downtown could
and would be reborn
as a business district.
- [Silverstein] And they looked at
what was going on across the street.
Havoc. I mean, just disaster
across the street, right?
They knowing it was the Port.
Here, we finished a building.
And all of a sudden,
people startled and said,
"What's he doing that's so bad?
What's he doing so wrong?
Maybe he's the problem."
People started looking and saying,
"Maybe it's he's not the problem."
[water flowing]
- [Arad] The design initially suggested
these Memorial galleries,
which would surround the pools
some 30 feet below the plaza.
And so the idea was that
you would walk up to the--
adrift of these voids,
sort of peer down below
and then go on this very,
you know, emotionally fraught
processional experience and sort of
walking into the area almost
walking right up to the names,
which would be displayed
behind the waterfalls in this
very sort of quiet, cloister-like space.
- [Rosaleen] In advocating
for the ranks of the firefighters,
we were invited to Michael Arad's office
to speak of that
and we were in the meeting room,
in the conference room,
and you know, all around were
aspects of the Memorial.
But there was a three dimensional model
of the Memorial.
And up to that point, none of us had really
questioned where the names were going.
But then we saw the three dimensional
model and we realized
the names were gonna be
underneath the waterfalls
at the base of the waterfalls,
underground.
You would have to descend down, almost
as though, you were going into the subway.
Descend down underground,
into a confined space to view the names.
And that shocked us.
Knowing now about 1993,
about 2001, I will never go down.
I will never bring my children
underground at Ground Zero
because I feel it's always gonna be the
number one target site of the terrorists.
They've come twice.
What better place than to get us
all while we're underground.
I mean, it just--
it never made sense to me.
- [Arad] It'll be so easy for this design
to be changed in a fundamental way.
And you know, while every
suggestion that was made,
was made by somebody who cares deeply
about the Memorial,
was not necessarily consistent
with the design that was selected
and then I felt it was my obligation
to champion and be responsible for it.
How do you build a moment of silence?
This is what this is.
- [speaker] Write down the ideas,
because you know, four hours from now--
This is America's Memorial,
as they all like to say.
America doesn't know what she's getting.
New York is on now, an American self now.
- [Man] That's insane.
- [Rosaleen] Thank you very much.
Do you know they're spending
$1.2 billion on this?
- [speaker] On a Memorial
that nobody wants.
- [Rosaleen] We bring out
the sleeping bags
and we bring out warmer clothes
to spend the night here.
9/11 families have always been
somewhat out in the public but
this was taking a step where people
could really be critical of you saying
that you had flipped your lid, you know.
And you know, you could feel that.
You could feel that,
"Maybe, I'm so deep into this.
Maybe, I'm carrying it too far."
But the first nights down there,
I knew that it was the right thing to do.
We looked out into the vast openness
and we could just say
this was their spot
and we're defending it.
- [Reporter] They're being touted
as the last pieces
in the rebirth of Lower Manhattan.
The three towers: 2, 3 and 4 will replace
about 6 million square feet
of the 10 million destroyed in the attack.
Norman Foster's tower is the largest
of the three buildings.
It's taller than the Empire State Building
and has diamond-like paneling
along the top.
Richard Roger's tower
is far sleeker in design.
Fumihiko Maki's is the first to be built,
will have a restaurant
with panoramic views.
- [Silverstein] Good morning.
- [speaker] Mr. Damian, you know.
- Hello, Damian.
- [Damian] Hi.
- HI, buddy. How are you?
Okay.
- [speaker] We're in deep discussion
with the Board
and the transit authority's
about that.
- [Silverstein] We have less congestion
by pulling this in
and having these out here.
All during this time, we're plowing ahead,
plowing ahead.
Because we have--Governor said
we design, finish plans,
specification and so forth
for Towers 2, 3 and 4.
We did them, 18 months we finished
the plans, specifications, done.
All right. Ready to go.
Ready to shovel the ground.
Is this width the same
as this width?
And guess what?
No ground on which to put a shovel.
Why? Because the sites aren't ready.
The sites the Port Authority's
suppose to deliver to us.
Not ready.
We know what it takes to dig a hole.
But for some reason, your people,
they're taking longer.
Much longer than it has
ever been taken, right?
What's taking so long?
- [Lieber] What happened was they had
another groundbreaking.
And they started construction of
this PATH Train Station,
designed by Santiago Calatrava.
- [Pataki] And I remember
the Port Authority had,
going to Santiago and saying,
"Is it expensive?" and he said,
"Of course, it is."
- [Raab] Okay, build me the world's
most expensive subway stop.
Two billion dollar?
No, make it $4 billion.
The wings are going to open
like a dove twice a year
or maybe not.
- [Lieber] And what increasingly became clear
is that this train station,
which they called, "The Oculus,"
because of its shape,
was actually an octopus that was
killing all the other projects around it
because they were sticking
all their mechanical system,
their air condition, their heating,
to support this train station,
were being pushed into other buildings.
It was creating all kinds
of complexities and delays.
- [David Paterson] In my perusal,
just in the first days of my administration,
I couldn't really find anyone that
knew what was being built,
who was building it,
when it would be completed
and how and what fashion
it would actually be erected.
- [worker] Wonderful time.
- [Chris Ward] Sir. Good.
- [Lieber] And one of the first things
that Paterson did when he came in,
was to replace the head
of the Port Authority
with a new guy named, Chris Ward.
- [Ward] It's great they're all tied off.
We wanted it to be symbolic.
We wanted it to be monumental.
That could've and should've
remained at a certain level,
but it became to dominate
the whole project literally
right down into the ground and when
it dominated it down into the ground,
the project lost its logic,
it lost its constructability.
- [Raab] Chris Ward's a guy who's
smart enough to come into the office
and recognize that
everyone had been lying.
Everyone had been
bullshitting for years.
Everyone had held press conferences,
and made promises,
and none of those press conferences
meant a goddamn thing
and none of those promises
could be kept.
- [Paterson] After looking at the
construction solutions,
that Chris Ward and the staff of
the Port Authority
have been able to establish,
I am comfortable today
by telling you that on
September 11th, 2011,
ten years to the date of that disaster,
there will be an open memorial
at Ground Zero to those
who lost their lives that day.
- [Ward] We made a major commitment
that the plaza would be open
on the ten-year anniversary.
The fountains would be functioning,
the water would fall
and that was the commitment we made.
But it was a lot more complicated
and there was some real fundamental
disconnects in what had to get built
and how it would get built
and who would build it, that had
to really get completely sorted out.
- [Silverstein] Things were sliding
further and further and further behind
as we progressed, right? As the days
went by, the days, the months.
- [Ward] The Mayor, advocate for the city,
saw that things were in fact, stalled,
took it upon himself to bring us
together in a Gracie Mansion Summit.
He brought the Governors together
from both States.
He brought Larry and he brought me there.
- [Bloomberg] When they're not
making progress, just shake things up.
You put them in a room with a
big pot of coffee
and lock the doors with no bathroom.
You'd be surprised how quickly
they come to an agreement.
- [Ward] It was one of those moments
that I'm sure the Mayor
was very, very disappointed,
if you go to Gracie Mansion,
the whole idea is you have success
when you leave.
But you couldn't on that day,
solve all the problems
as the Mayor had hoped we would.
- [Lieber] At some point, you know,
the anger gives way to just depression
because you think, "How are we gonna
ever get out of this?"
[crowd cheering and applauding]
- [speaker] Let me hear you
one more time.
Wouldn't we want these jobs?
[crowd shouting] No!
- [speaker] The finger pointing
has got to stop.
That's almost nine years after 9/11,
instead of a shiny symbol of
American resilience and strength,
we have a hole in the ground.
[cheering and applause]
- [Lieber] The construction workers
in New York were so out of work.
At this point, this six months
after Lehman Brothers went down
and we're in the middle
of this incredible economic collapse.
- [Ward] And you could take a
pessimistic view and go,
"You know, maybe this worldwide recession
is gonna be deep.
It's gonna be long and that we're not
gonna come out of it quickly."
We had a study that said,
"Maybe the market's not back
all the way until 2037.
- [Lieber] People were not down for
waiting another 25 years
to get the World Trade Center rebuilt.
[crowd chanting] Build it now!
Build it now!
- [Ward] It was kind of a great moment
because everybody's chanting,
"Build it now!" And I was like,
"Who are they talking to?"
They were talking to me because
I was the one guy who was there
that would answer the question,
"Could you build it now?"
They were convinced that we were
the ones who were slowing it down.
- [speaker] We need the Hirsch, Chris,
Larry, the city, to get back at the table
to find a solution so that these
two towers can be built
and they can be built now.
- [Lieber] No more excuses. It's time
for us to all put our shoulders
so that we all work together
to get the job done.
And I think that was a game changer.
- [Paterson] And today, we have found
an agreement
that we feel will allow us
to complete the reconstruction
of the World Trade Center's site.
- [Ward] Wow. This is progress.
This is probably the most important
part of the project from the
Port Authority's commitment to
deliver the plaza for the anniversary.
We have to have this done or
the plaza will not be completed.
But you stand here and think,
"Are they gonna be able
to get it all done?"
We're doing really well. I have no
expectation that we won't deliver
but, imagine it if we don't?
- [Jim] What's up, V.?
- [V.] How's it going, Jim?
How are you, buddy?
- [worker] I got it right here.
The one coming through
from this way here is sided.
- [Jim] Okay, all right.
[crackling metal sound]
I gotta get all the way out to the street
five feet by today, alright?
Bob, we need those two
beehive strainers.
When you look at it like this,
it's just amazing how many
people killed that day.
Well, I lost my mother on 9/11.
She was on the 94th floor
of the North Tower.
I don't know what to say.
That's just hard to imagine
it's ten years already. It really is.
It's what we have right here.
- [Arad] Reading the names
up to the plaza,
when that decision was made
against my wishes,
it felt like a tremendous blow.
And you know-- but if it is a child,
if it is your child and it's injured,
you don't walk away from it,
you stay involved. You keep caring.
My hope is when the memorial opens up,
whatever dissatisfaction's had been
expressed up until now, some of this
here's might be assuaged.
We'll see, I mean that's the missing
ingredient for the memorial right now,
it's that interaction between
the public and the memorial.
And what you have right now is
the stage that's set for that encounter.
SEPTEMBER 11, 2011
[crickets chirping]
Bye, sweetie. I'm leaving now.
[door opens
then closes]
You know, last night at 11:00 or so,
all of a sudden I sort of had this urge
to jump in the car and drive to see the site
to make sure that everything's there.
You know, sort of last minute--
You wanna make sure
everything is just right.
[Sean giggling]
- [Sean] Ahh...
- [Rosaleen] Sean?
[scraping sound]
You put on Uncle Sean's shirt?
You can put on Uncle Sean's shirt.
- [Arad] Today's gonna be
really difficult.
But it's the moment I've been waiting for.
- [Judey] I want that one, please.
- [Rosaleen] Please have
a couple of bites, Sean.
I'll give Panny then, a little bit
of your English muffin.
- [Sean] They had a truck in those
bunks in the truck
and they move it into the garage.
- [Rosaleen] You know, Daddy went
over there to see
if he could find Uncle Sean.
I don't know if you ever knew that.
- [Judey] He did?
- [Rob Tallon] Yeah.
- I never knew that.
- [Rosaleen] It would be nice
to see Uncle Sean's name, right?
- [Judey] Yeah.
- [Silverstein] Thank you.
[car door closes]
- [Rosaleen] Guys,
ain't it a beautiful day?
- [Eileen] Oh, yes.
- They had predicted rain for
yesterday and today.
- [Silverstein] Go on,
just go pass them slowly.
Go further.
You're gonna go straight to Denmar.
- [woman] Good morning.
- [driver] Good morning, ma'am.
- How are you?
- [Silverstein] Silverstein!
- Straight ahead, Sir.
- Thank you.
- Okay. - [driver] Thank you.
- Have a great day.- Likewise, ma'am.
- [Eileen] He was just beaming that
morning. He was all lit up
in the house, had such a smile.
He was wearing his lovely shirt
and then he's got on him a white collar
and he just looks so good and smiling.
- [Rosaleen] Yes, they are very charming.
Where's Grandma?
Keep Grandma with us.
- [Judey] Can you release my hand.
[footsteps]
- [Bloomberg] Please join in observing
our first moment of silence.
[bell dings]
- [speaker 1] Edelmiro Abad
- [speaker 2] Vincent Paul Abate
- Laurence Christopher Abel
- Albert Balewa Blackman, Jr.
- Christopher Joseph Blackwell
- Carrie Rosetta Blagburn
- Susan Leigh Blair
♪ [melancholy music] ♪
- [Arad] It's easy to think about all the
strife, all the disagreement,
to sort of focus on, "Well, you know,
this didn't go right, that didn't go right."
Actually, the big picture is something
went right, really right.
- [Silverstein] At the end of the day,
it's a good thing to see,
everything out moving down the track
and getting built because
this is important to New York.
You have to develop very thick skin,
really take a long view,
a very long view.
And praises? White noise.
- [Rosaleen] That's Sean's name.
I mean, he's one of these people
listed on this memorial.
That's the shocker, I think.
You know, you say,
"God, that was my flesh and blood
that got caught up in all of this."
- [Lieber] I don't know if the city
will ever be whole.
The people who are lost,
the families who experienced that.
You can never put that back or replace,
but there's a part of the city's self respect
that I think is gonna be restored.
- [Childs] This is not Rome,
in which you wanna hold it as it now is,
as a great historic monument,
but something which evolves and changes.
That's the nature of New York.
- [Philip] It's an incredibly healthy thing
that the city responded
to September 11th in sort of,
classic New York fashion
by beating each other up and
grandstanding in political manipulation
and you can say, "Oh, that's awful."
Or you can say, "What a wonderful thing
that New York
healed this big wound with more New York."
Citing marketing concerns,
the Port Authority renamed
the "Freedom Tower"
1 World Trade Center.
Soon after, the agency signed
a lease for 1 million square feet
of office space with magazine
publisher Condé Nast.
The building will be the tallest
in the city and is expected
to open in 2014, ten years after
the cornerstone ceremony.
Chris Ward was pushed out
of his job at the Port Authority
and replaced by a top aide
to Governor Andrew Cuomo.
7 World Trade Center reached
full occupancy in October 2011.
Larry Silverstein hopes to complete
the World Trade Center project
by 2016, when he'll be 85 years old.
4 WTC will be the first tower
to open on the site in 2013.
The completion dates for 2 and 3 WTC
depend on the success of
Silverstein's leasing efforts.
Since winning the master-plan
competition in 2003, Daniel Libeskind
has designed more than 40 projects
around the world,
including several skyscrapers.
The cornerstone now rests
behind the headquarters of the
company that engraved it,
in Hauppauge, Long Island.