[music]
- We welcome, Ms. Joan Rivers!
[applause]
- You know, you're going to be
a big star.
- Here's my dappy, little friend,
Joan Rivers!
[screaming]
[applause]
- Joan Rivers,
the groundbreaking
female comedian
paved the way for women ---
[applause]
- The Grammy goes to...
Joan Rivers!
[applause]
- We hear Joan Rivers!
- ___ and I'm very, very late.
[music]
- Keep bringing 'em,
you're gonna need them.
Welcome, Ms. Joan Rivers!
[applause]
- This is my career.
How depressing is this.
[laughter]
Forty years in
the fucking business
and this is where you end up.
[audience laughter]
Just to show you...
My daughter and I are very close;
very, very close.
But I brought her up all wrong.
I brought her up to have morals.
She turned down doing
Playboy magazine cover,
how about that?
Four hundred thousand dollars,
naked to the waist.
Turned it fuckin' down
and calls me up for approval.
For approval!
"Mother, I turned down
Playboy. What do you think?"
And you know, what do I think?
I'm very proud of you, Melissa.
What do I think?
What do I think,
you stupid, fucking cunt!
What do I think?
[audience laughter]
I think you should ask
200,000 more
and show your pussy!
That's what I think!
[audience applause and laughter]
I'm a 75 year old woman
I'll be ___ drums in Queens!
What do I think?
[audience laughter]
I'm not a fucking red __
with a hot stunt
----
where are you from?
Got a lucky charm.
Who the fuck are you?
[audience applause and laughter]
[music]
A year in the life of
a semi-legend.
- Not good. This is not good.
We have no Vegas, no giant club date.
Kathy Griffin's taken all
those away.
I have the play, which is
not giving me any money.
Can we get club gigs?
Can't Billy get club gigs?
And this is not a full book.
- Like a little date here and there.
- Yeah.
- Sure.
- These were the good years.
- See this is the kind of a book I like.
Now that's a good page.
You know what I mean?
Ten o'clock, eleven o'clock.
Twelve thirty, this and that.
That's happiness.
Last year was a very difficult year.
I was playing Here We Go,
the Bronx at 4:30 in the afternoon.
That was a real good one.
I'll show you fear.
That's fear.
If my book ever looked like this,
it would mean that nobody wants me,
That everything I ever tried to do
in life didn't work.
Nobody cares and I've been
totally forgotten.
- When you say Joan, I get ___
hold on let me put my sunglasses on
because the white of the page
hurts my eyes.
So, that's a joke.
So we used to laugh at that.
"Hold on, let me get my sunglasses."
Okay, what day?
- You don't have to.
- Humor me.