There are all sorts of dangers.
Postal workers, fire men, police officers,
everything has a risk to it.
I will prefer personally to have
a challenging, stimulating, emotionally
and spiritually rewarding,uhh, career
that is short, rather than have a long one
that's filled with mediocrity,
feeling as if you don't make
any difference to people.
[women talking over the phone]
- Tiller has performed
legal abortion since 1973.
His Women's Healthcare Services Clinic
is just one of three in the nation.
which perform late term abortion
up to the twenty-first week of pregnancy.
[Woman talking on the phone]
- For more than two decades
George Tiller was a target
of anti abortion extremists,
which he thought when
it was bombed in 1985.
In 1993 he was shot in both arms,
and then at the age of 67
he was murdered at churh.