- the american west sea
- but people began finding
- and they spread out
- for this is the story of the miracle sea in the desert
- the Salton Sea
- 385 square miles of water formed by accident back in 1905 when the Colorado River ran wild over man-made dikes
- a sea in the desert with its white sandy beaches
- The Salton Sea, the new recreational capital of the world
- The future is now and you, you have been present at the birth of a city.
-[ water gushing]
- That is a combination sort of things
- trust, caring, honesty, which honesty is the biggest thing
- And i'll just bet my bottom dollar, it's a beautiful hue to see your dad give your mama hug and a kiss.
- If you see love between your parents, even if it's just once in a while, that will install love in you.
- If you dont, you're gonna be alone, lonesome dude in a faraway place.
- The desert is very unforgiving.
- It has no mercy on anybody or anyone
To live on, you have to improvise
in order to survive.
wooo!! where's the dead bird?
Is that dead?
eeew! you want a piece of gum
we're gonna have to climb over here
we're greounded for 1 week for throwing rocks at another child
you're fighting on the bus
and you threw a rock
remember that?
you hit her in the head and made her bleed
that was her head? I thought that was William his head was bleeding
there was more than one. There was 3 actually
I know waht this is for
what?
This is for the cut. This thing is for --- and the black one is..
This one is rhinalene. What this one does.. knowing you run around a lot and you can't stop moving and you're very hyper. this is supposed to make you where you don't do that. it calms you down.
Is that new mom?
No it's not new. He's been taking that for almost 2 years. and this one, Resperto, is for..
Crazy..
No, you're not crazy sweetie. I never think you're crazy, ok?
- ♪ Happy Birthday ♪
- [children singing]
- Make a wish!
- Benny what'd you wish for?
- I wish for mom and dad to love me all year long
- [children enjoying and laughing]
- are you ready?
- yes
- Are you ready?
- No. Yeees!
- [Pop music playing]
- Let's get it on!
Bring it.. bring it!
- [Laughter]
- [sea breeze blowing]
- I left home when I was 13
My father told me many years ago, the harder you work the richer you will die
It's riches what you have learned by experience or in hundred dollars that you can get in the bank
Around, a lot of places in the south west part of the country here, The state cannot tax the indian reservation for cigarettes
So they sell 'em a little cheaper. So if you buy 'em there, you can bootleg a few of them, and make a few pennies' profit.
Well, you might say well, that's illegal. You have to figure out a way, at your golden age, to support yourself at least partially.
- Where's your master, huh?
- Hey justin..you know where jerry is?
- No, I don't.
- I guess i haven't seen him since wednesday
- I'll be the last --- bill gets on me
- I got damn 300 dollars phone bill this month
- At the desert, has a lot of poor people. For different reasons, they are poor. They wanna bum a cigarette.
- Sometimes a run --- makes me. I've been that way all my life. But I sure enjoyed it.
- ♪ [background song] ♪
- woooh! oh! Off-road golf cart drivin. Left turn...
- Jump that hole!
- I got this! I've got.. I got!
- Shnnng,shng shng shng..
- I'm drivin..
- Is that a bar in here?
- C'mo
- Can I see the... the menu?
- Cheeseburger and onion rings 'n hamburger fries
- [piano playing]
- Time to get up dude
- What happened?
- uh, --- just a mistake, no one lookin or whatever and..
- He just kept going? He hit you?
- Most people do.
- Did he-- what d hell-- he was hurting your back or your arm?
- Can you move your leg?
- No, that's fine... my shoulder... my arm...
- It'll heal... It'll heal...
- You need a doctor or somethin...
- You need to get up... Well if you wanna lay down just lay down.
- please don't tell...
- we're not... we're not
- all right... all right...
- I'll handle it.
- You're ok? You all right?
- Thank you. I'll remember your face though.
- His arm is broken, can you see it?
- Probably...
- All right here's Brooke. I'm not gonna touch it.
- Is your arm broken?... here? You gotta go in the hospital now and get it looked at.
- I'll take care of it.
- If you start bleeding inside, you'll bleed to death.
- Thank God!
- Eight, nine, fifteen, seventeen, eighteen, thirty
- Not ready..
- It's
- Hey, How did you know we're up there?
How did you get up there?
- [children screaming]
- Hurry up and hide!
- Can I use the flashlight, that's not hide and seek.
- Ten, nine, eight, seven, six, five, four, three, two, one
- [explosion]
- K-S-W-T TV 13 Weekend news.
- Sherriff's deputies recovered the explosives of an ammunition in an island home.
- Police first responded to the home to investigate a child neglect case and found a porable conditions inside the home along with explosive.
- Authorities arrested the couple who lived there Michael and Pamela Parrish.
- The Parrish family like to play army. FBI attempted to get a mysterious-- I remember this is one year after 9-11.
- Even though it occurred in August 2002,After we had a heavy rain, it uncovers a lot of the ordinance that has been been covered with dirt or buried.
- Ahh damn.
- we can go ba
- [explosion]
- Those people are doing good.
- They are.They're doing good.
- hard to believe it's the same Parrish family you know.
- [razor running]
Sometimes I think what else can we do with our family here because there's nothing.
- All we could do is choriding in the desert, shoot guns. But we can't do that anymore
- Child Protective Services already took the kids twice. So if they take them again for the 3rd time, they told us that we would never see them again.
- How does know why CPS are here
- Sabrina told me that she saw 'em at her house when they drove by and they're counting cars and sheriffs.
- And if they're gonna take kids away, there's gonna be a sheriff there coz they can't take them without a sheriff.
- Yeah, 3 sheriffs there.
- I know so... [sigh]... But you know what, we're not doing anything wrong.
- And your house is being, you know, cleaned. So if they come, all you need to do is tell them the truth.
- Or just say...
- You're happy? You have a house?
- Or just say... I'm beggin you, I'm sorry.
- Please don't take me.
- After we got back from prison and we got the kids back, I noticed Benjamin was a little different than the other children.
- This is my bunny, huh, because I'm a girl. This is my backpack. Funny mom. I'm a girl.
- I'll be back soon Harry. I can go to school like Clayene nicely.
- yeah you can.
- I can say, hello pretty girl. I love you!
- ahm hm hm wow how about that... you can say hi.
- What's this mommy? A bullet.
- Well that's a bullet.
- Can I see it, Can I have it.
- Throw that over there, ok.
- Can I throw it in the water?
- No.
- Because it will scare fish?
- It might!
- Look at the wave.
-I know they're real far
-I'm not goin the wave
- I think they're gonna be big this time.
- Ain't gonna go in the big wave.
- Yeah
-Well you don't have to hold me. You can watch
- I won't let you down.
- Because you will run here quick.
- I'm not really swimmin like a dolphin.
- Dolphins are goin here, huh.
- No, it's too salty, I think they're in the ocean
- Is this an ocean?
- No, it's just a sea.
- That fish I hate that fish coz if I step on them, It will get inside my shoes and inside my foot.
- What kind of fish would you be if you could be a fish?
- A fish
- What king of fish? Like a silly fish or purple or..
- A happy fish!
- I think I will be a happy fish, too.
- I could barely force water down
- That, is a salad!
- I baked a hundred and fifty pork chops. So I think we have enough.
- Cm here You smell rookie.
- You better
- I ain't gonna be sexy with you, I just wanna smell you.
- It's gonna cost you a dollar
- Can't I charge a pay till night? I Just wanna get my money, you know.
- [bleep] If I charge cigarette I wouldn't be--
- Ah no, blah blah blah blah
- blah blah me! The hell with it.
- Because [bleep] this old man you still owe me up today
- Hey,
- yeah, for a cool minute.
-like that?
- Maybe
- Go mess around and pop some fireworks.