[music]
- We welcome, Ms. Joan Rivers!
[applause]
- You know, you're going to be
a big star.
- Here's my dappy, little friend,
Joan Rivers!
[screaming]
[applause]
- Joan Rivers,
the groundbreaking
female comedian
paves the way for women
everywhere ---
now iI know who is gay
and who isn't gay --
can we talk to you?
[applause]
- The Grammy goes to...
Joan Rivers!
[applause]
- Here's Joan Rivers!
- and I'm very, very late.
[music]
-I hope you had a few drinks
cuz you're gonna need them.
Welcome, Ms. Joan Rivers!
[applause]
- This is my career.
How depressing is this?
[laughter]
Forty years in
the fucking business
and this is where you end up.
[audience laughter]
Just to show you...
My daughter and I are very close;
very, very close.
But I brought her up all wrong.
I brought her up to have morals.
She turned down doing
Playboy magazine cover,
how about that?
Four hundred thousand dollars,
naked to the waist.
Turned it fuckin' down
and calls me up for approval.
For approval!
"Mother, I turned down
Playboy. What do you think?"
And you know, what do I think?
I'm very proud of you, Melissa.
What do I think?
What do I think,
you stupid, fucking cunt!
What do I think?
[audience laughter]
I think you should ask
200,000 more
and show your pussy!
That's what I think!
[audience applause and laughter]
I'm a 75 year old woman
I'll be playing the drums in Queens!
What do I think?
[audience laughter]
I'm on a fucking red carpet
in the hot sun
talking to these assholes
where are you from?
Got a lucky charm.
Who the fuck are you?
[audience applause and laughter]
[music]
- Not good. This is not good.
We have no Vegas, no giant club date.
Kathy Griffin's taken all
those away.
I have the play, which is
not going to give me any money.
Can we get club dates?
Can't Billy get club dates?
And this is not a full book.
- Like a little date here and there.
- Yeah.
- Sure.
- These were the good years.
- See this is the kind of a book I like.
Now that's a good page.
You know what I mean?
Ten o'clock, eleven o'clock.
Twelve thirty, this and that.
That's happiness.
Last year was a very difficult year.
I was playing Here We Go,
the Bronx at 4:30 in the afternoon.
That was a real good one.
I'll show you fear.
That's fear.
If my book ever looked like this,
it would mean that nobody wants me,
That everything I ever tried to do
in life didn't work.
Nobody cared and I've been
totally forgotten.
- When you say Joan, get out your
calendar she says hold on on
let me put my sunglasses on
because the white of the page
hurts my eyes.
So, that's a joke.
So we used to laugh at that.
"Hold on, let me get my sunglasses."
Okay, what day?
[music].
You look handsome.
Yeah right.
Billy looks good and he can't
stand it. I can't.
Why not?
My career is in the toliet
That's me.
My career is in the toilet
nothing is going right,
that's right
Nothing.
Why?
Why not?
I don't know it's like
ya know?
That's what I always
tell them.
That still gets me.
Billy Sabbath is a big
part of my life
a huge part of my life.
He knows my history
there are so few people
that you can say, do you
remember Bernie Billstein
-and we both laugh
and laugh.
-Joan is a chronic
workaholic.
-one job a day is not
enough it's almost like
an addict.
Sadly, but she's a
work addict
-so it's not enough no
matter how much you
give her it doesn't
fill up that need to
-be working.
Now this is Joslin Picket,
this is my assistant
who is not going to
show you how busy I am.
Anybody call?
No.
It's not about whether
the talent is good
-it's about whether
they're hot.
There are times in
people's careers
that you just can't
get it going.
Careers do that, you're
hot, you're not,
-you're in a slump
you're not.
Nothing is happening
right now, so she
-needs some heat.
-Steve Laean's office.
Jennifer Mowen
Hi Billy Sabbath.
-and Joan Rivers.
Hi Joan Rivers, hold
on just a moment.
-Hello.
I's get through
-faster if I was
Kathy Griffin.
-Hello. Hi.
Let's hear about Harrod's
-which is May 18th which the
weekend before Memorial Day.
I just think it's
wrong.
It's not vacation,
the kids are still
-in school.
I want a letter from
-from them saying we
acknowledge the worst
-weekend, one of the
worst weekends of the
-year.
And i really don't
-need at this age, when
I'm a comedy icon
-I don't need to walk
into a room and have
-it half full and
then have the
-Harris people go
cluck, cluck, cluck.
Right now they see her
as a plastic surgery
-freak who's past due
her, you know, her
-sell by date.
Who's finished.
But God help the next
Queen of Comedy
-because this one is
not abdicating.
Never will. There will
be nail marks on that
-red carpet before she
abdicates.
So good luck to the
next Queen.
Happy Birthday to you.
Age is the one mountain
that you can't overcome.
It's a youth society and
nobody wants you. Your too
-old, you're too old.
If one more woman
-comedian comes to me
and says to me, you opened
the doors for me and you
want to say,
-go fuck yourself.
I'm still opening the
-doors.
Thank you very much.
You are a Barnard College
graduate ? Yes.
And your father's a
doctor. Yes.
You live, where?
Scarsdale?
In Large Mouth.
And your mother is a?
A mother.
Just a mother.
[audience laughs].
How do they look upon
this, what you're doing?
What it is that you do?
Frightened.
[audience laughs]
Well now they are very
show biz.
And my mother and I
are thinking of doing
-a sister act. But ummm
[audience laughs].
The audience here really
liked ya and good luck
-to ya.
[clapping].
Joan here is a script
for the TV pilot, you
-wanted to look at.
Ok, do you know where
-I am in this?
[phone ringing].
I see no Joan on page 2,
I see no Joan on page 3.
I see no Joan on page 4.
[laughs].
I have worked with her
for about 15 years,
I think, somewhere in
there, so I definately
-have gone through kind
of the ups and downs,
-you know with her career.
When I started it was
definitely kind of a
lower point,
-her daytime talk show,
was cancelled at the
-same time her play,
Sally Mar which ran on
Broad Way. That shut
down. Everything was
kind of closing at that
point.
So of course Joan
being Joan started
to reinvent herself.
No, I ain't seeing me.
This year is no
different.
Joan is looking at
new projects,
-new ways to get out
there.
She's got 2 new books
coming out.
A new play that she's
really worked very hard
for the past couple
of years.
And Celebrity Apprentice,
she's booked to be on the
next series of
Celebrity Apprentice.
So she's hoping one of
them hits and puts her
back on top.
I can't find me
anywhere.
[music].
[horns blowing].
What we are planning is
the cut-off date for
-the Tony Nominations
is somewhere in April,
-so we have to open
somewhere in April.
The next few months
I am really focusing
-just on my play.
It means a great deal
-to me because it tells
my life story.
So she calls me up
and she goes
Billy its Joan, listen
I wrote a script a
couple of years ago,
it's in the drawer.
I actually saw a reading
of it a year earlier
-and I enjoyed it.
So I said I think
-you should do it.
Hi Joanie.
Hi Billy boy.
[kissing].
[background conversations]
Schmidtie, how you doing?
Schmidt Schmidt, Schmidt
The name of the show is
Joan Rivers -
A Work in Progress by
A Life in Progress.
Episodes from her life.
How she got to where she
-is now. We're going to
take this to the
-Edmonds Festival, and
then we're going to do
-it in London's Glittering
West End.
The ultimate goal, I think
Joan wants to play it
-in her home town.
I have very few hairs left
on my head and each one has
-a name, like last week
we Shiva for Bernice.
We buried Bernice.
We cremated Bernice.
Yeah cremated Bernice.
I hope that the play
-is a huge success.
I think the play will
-remind them I am an
actress, I'm a writer.
And if we get great
reviews,
-it will open up a million other
things.
One of my earliest
memories must have been
-top 6 years old, my
mother took me to see
-Paul Ropes in Longfellow and
I remember smelling the smells
-of the theater and I
thought, this is where
-I belong.
I was in every school
-play. I was in
everything that you could
-do in college. I was never a
discussion in my own head
of where I was going.
I was always acting.
I was always going to
be an actress.
You were straight acting
or comedy, or --
No, no comedy never.
I just knew that I
-could work the comedian
at night and make money to
-make the rounds as an
actress. And that's the
only reason I went
into comedy.
Sometimes I sit at
home and I think to
-myself, Joan, yes
your're a diva,
-you're a diva.
Penthouse, limos,
-furs, woof, woof.
But a diva can get
-lonely. And I say this
to my staff. I say, staff
[laughter].
I don't learn their
-names like you people
they come, they go.
Sometimes I say to them
staff, I'm lonely.
Who's going to fuck
me tonight?
[laughter].
Yes, yes, yes,
-this is delicious, huh?
This is Kevin who runs
my house also, without
asking me anything.
Thank God. That is
Debbie, his wife,
-over there who is really
the brains behind Kevin
-just thought you should
know.
[laughs].
It's bacon, you idiot.
This is my apartment and it's
very grand. This is how
Marie Antoinette would
have lived if she had
-had money.
[music].
You try to explain to
people before you go to
-nobody lives like this.
Maybe the Queen of England.
-but besides that, nobody
lives like this.
I live very very very
well. That's to start
-with. I enjoy my
creature comforts and
-I know I have to work for
it. I could stop and live
-carefully, but that's
ridiculous, I don't want
-to live carefully. So I
would rather work and live
-the way I live at one
whole time.
When I hear the numbers
from her accountant,
-you know behind our client's
back everyone is whispering
-so they called and said
Billy, you got a pull
-another rabbit out of the
hat. How many rabbits would
-you like out of the hat?
I don't have that many more
-rabbits in my hat.
When I first hit on
-The Carson Show, years
ago, my manager was a man
-named Jack Rollins and he
said you're going to be
-an industry.
When people hit, they
become industries and
that's really it, I'm a
small industry.
Checks for you to sign.
Oh good, okay.
I have an agent, I have
a manager, I have a
-business manager,
a PR lady, 2 assistants,
and a lawyer.
Don't forget the lawyers.
There are then,
relatives that I'm
-totally supporting.
Certain friends, most
-people that work with me
if they have children
-I send the children to
private schools.
It goes on, on, on, on
and on.
I'm dancing as fast as
I can.
[laughs].
Are you on speaker?
I am.
So where do we start?
Joan they want you for
125,000 dollars for 3 days,
where you can
-tie it in and sell your
jewelry. Should I sign it?
Yes I'd love to, because
I'm very short on money.
Trust me, we need it.
Okay. Okay.
How about bump up the
offer and you'll do your
-comedy.
Yeah, bump up the offer
-and they get Joan
on stage.
Bump up the offer some
more and they get Joan
doing survival lecture and
on stage. Bump up the
-offer some more and they also
get the red carpet lecture.
The survival lecture. And
don't forget just the
125 grand worth of charm.
[laughs]
[music].
[bird singing].
You know the dates we are
hosting QVC, right Billy?
Pretty much. Yeah.
Let me ask you last
-thing. Do you think it's
in bad taste to say that
Obama's wife, who I think is
so shiek, Michelle, that she
-is, remember the old days
the Kennedy Era there was
-the Jackie O?
Well in the Obama Era
-it's going to be Blackie O.
Oh no. Okay just thought
it was a great joke.
These are all my jokes.
These are jokes over the
-last 30 years.
Every time I write a
-joke, I try to remember to
put it on a card.
Why should a woman cook?
So her husband can say
-my wife makes a delicious
cake to some hooker.
[laughs].
And you wonder why I'm still
-working at this age.
People think it comes so
-easily, they have no idea
what you're doing is a
-terrifically difficult thing
to do and I prepare like a
-crazy lady.
I mean here I am, everything
-is just everywhere you
look, there are jokes.
-jokes to be filed, jokes
to be written, jokes that
-I thought of something.
I mean my life is just
-jokes.
Vagina farts are so loud, my
gynecologist wears ear plugs.
[laughs].
Are gay men proud of their
excessive body hair,
-like Madonna's daughter.
Amazing race, Mel Gibson
chasing Jews into
-the showers.
[laughs].
As some of you can tell now,
I'm 7 1/2 months pregnant.
-and you want to know the
truth?
At night when I'm undressed
and my husband looks at me
-and mentally dresses me.
[laughs].
When I started comedy I was
very wild for the time,
-but different times.
The last line of my original
act was "This business it's
all about casting characters.
So I just want you to know my
-name is Joan Rivers and I
put out.
And you would hear the
audience, such a sweet
-little silly line from a
girl who is 28 years old
-you know,dressed up trying
to look nice.
Half of them laughed, Jack
Lemon saw me and walked out.
He said that's disgusting.
So for my time I was very
-shocking. I remember I had
a joke about abortions when you
weren't supposed to even say
the word on television.
I have a friend who just got
married. The woman is
-32 years old, she had 14
appendectomies, if you know
-what I'm telling you.
You know,back and forth
-to Puerto Rico, she never
stopped flying.
She walked down the aisle in
white. Every usher went --
[laughs].
My manager took me out and said
to me, Joaniah, you're going
-into places you shouldn't
go. It's not right.
Women shouldn't talk about that.
I remember thinking you are
-so wrong.
This exactly what we should
-be talking about.
My daughter loves me very
very much.
I was there when she gave
birth, uck.
In California they bring the
parents in to see the birth.
Uck, uck, uck.
My day having a child
-was better.
They knocked you out with
-the first pain. They woke
you up in the hair dresser's
show, you knew nothing, it
was so much better.
Ms. Rivers you had a girl.
Good, good, good. [laughs].
Is she normal? Yeah. Good.
Is she white? Yeah. Good.
[laughing and clapping].
The marriage continues.
[laughs].
I went to see her live one time.
The shit that came out of her
-mouth was so shocking
and so funny, she was
-doing something, no other
woman was doing.
You know, I wouldn't be doing
this if it wasn't for Joan.
Much in the way that she
acknowledges Phyllis Diller
-paved the way for her. And
before her was Moms Mabley,
I get it, there is a handful
of women in modern history
-that have done this.
Just a handful.
I was so angry about --
Thank you.
Thank you, thank you.
While we're on the subject
let me talk to you about
-sex over 60, after 60, the body
drops.
My body, yeah, and it's not
just the breasts.
Vaginas drop.
Six years ago I woke up
-one morning and I said,
why am I wearing a
-bunny slipper
and why is it gray.
Brilliant.
I went to the dermatologist
so please excuse the way
-I look.
[laughs].
I shot filled with everything.
I said I needed ______.
Where did you go?
She just went crazy.
Lost her way.
And she said here
-go to rehearsal.
[laughs].
Okay, thank you Pat.
My mother told me
looks don't count.
She told me this a lot.
Saturday nights,
-in our kitchen
while I was growing up.
My mother used to look at
me and say [laughs].
Looks don't count. Now get
out of my sight, you big lump.
[laughs].
And my mother lied because --
It's very scary when you see
yourself totally without any
-makeup, it's really --
it gives me the willies.
Who is that person?
So I get up in the morning
and the first thing I do is
-is I get into makeup.
Now I was never the natural
beauty.
No man has ever ever told me
I'm beautiful.
They say to me you look great,
you look this, your terrific.
But no man has ever said,
on my God you're so beautiful.
[music].
Yeah. Bring them right in.
Yeah. Good. Yeah, good.
Okay, let's do tools.
Yeah, that's great.
Yeah, good.
People want to look at
pretty women.
Nobody wants an old
woman.
So I started with the
plastic surgery,
-little bits and tweaks.
And then I got very angry,
because nobody
-would admit it.
I really became a big
advocate of it.
And then I became the poster
girl for it.
And then I became the
joke of it.
Yeah, that's it.
Good.
So how did you come up with
the title?
Mel LaRue told that to me,
Yeah. At a party.
Yeah. Do you remember having
a discussion before we went
-on the air today?
right.
I said if you don't feel good
about yourself on the inside
-plastic surgery will not help
at all.
And in fact, can make things
worse.
Because then you think people
aren't really appreciating
-the real me.
Well who is the real me?
Tell me --
You are the real me.
We want to be loved for our sense
of humor, for our soul,
for our sweetness,
for our vulnerability,
for our intelligence. Yes?
I just want to be loved.
[music.]
I met Edgar.
I had been on the
-Carson Show.
Edgar called and he said
-to Johnnie, who do you know
who is a good writer?
And Carson said there was a
girl writer on last week.
You should look her up.
I met him, I married him
-four years later.
Was I madly in love
-with him? No.
Was it a good marriage?
Yes.
I thought marriage was
-going to be hugging and
kissing like in the movies.
You walk hand in hand, over
the hill into the sunset.
You know what's on the other
side of that hill?
Filthy dishes, that's what.
And socks.
How the last show last night?
Very good as a matter of fact.
Good.
Without Edgar I could never
-have done it.
We worked together.
We worked on projects together
so it was a family business.
Any woman that has a child
and doesn't yell
-is a fool, don;t you think?
Didn't you yell?
Why not? No.
It's your one chance to
-be noticed.
When I was having my
-kid, you should
[screams}.
[laughter].
And that was just during
conception.
I was dying to be a mother.
I couldn't wait to
-a mother.
And I really worked very
-hard to be there for her.
Of course, I'm sure she
felt very deserted as a
child, but I was there as
-much as I could be and
I made sure we were a
-family unit and she it.
What was it like living with
a legend?
Like yeah, it was hilarious
when I was getting grounded.
Which is why I always say
to people, you don't
-realize how in these very
extraordinary abnormal
-circumstances what a
normal world my parents
-created.
And that's a testiment
-to them.
It's funny because she
-refers to her career as
"THE" career, and it dawned
-on me one day, I had
a sibling. We all were
-on "The Career" as if
it was a totally separate
-entity in the room.
Melissa, what was your mom's
reaction when you told her
-you wanted to go into
show business?
Well what was the saying,
supportive,
-yet not encouraging.
Yeah, and still am.
Which is a little late in
the game to be supportive
and not encouraging.
It's such a hard
-business, what I tried
to do was protect her.
This is the one business
in the world, it is total
-rejection. I'm 75 and I'm
still rejected.
This business you are mud
your whole life.
[applause].
Josie Josie, you there?
Yes.
Have you heard from Billy?
I haven't I have gotten
-no calls back.
All right, can you
-send him an email?
I really want him there
-to see the play before we
go to Edinborough.
I mean there's Edinborough,
there's London, my God.
He's gotta see the play.
Okay, I'll email him as well.
So that's my manager Billy,
who I adore, disappears
-all the time.
3 years ago it was very
-very bad and I almost
fired him then and then
-your it's God, it's you
know.
I've known Billy, it's
gotta be about 35 years.
I could open the drawer
here somewhere and you'll
-find pictures of Billy.
Here look, young Billy.
Young Joan and Edgar in
the background.
Billy is part of my life and
I want to see him now, because
-we are doing the play and I
need another pair of eyes,
I need another brain. I need
his input desperately.
Welcome, welcome, welcome.
To what will be Joan River's
-A Work in Progress, by
a life in progress.
Okay, here we go.
I am thrilled to be
-here. I just don't want
this to be about me, me,
-me, me me. Hey Joan.
Not yet honey.
Again, you 2 back,
go back.
[laughs].
Anyhow, line, now where
was I?
[laughing and clapping].
Bill Cosby, who is a very
good friend of mine was on
-the Tonight Show and the
comic that was on with Bill
-absolutely bombed and Bill, God
bless him went over to the
-director and he said listen
why don't you use Joan Rivers
-she can't be any worse
than the guy that was on
-tonight.
And that's how they put
me on the next night.
And it was one of those
nights. Do you know like
-when everything goes right?
When the stars are in
alignment and the
-audience we just
connected.
And Carson at the end of
the act, after 9 years
-of working bungalow
colonies,and
-strips joints and working
in Greenwich Village
-in clubs where you pass
the hat and the hat
-wouldn't come back.
On the air, Carson said
to me you're going to be
-a star.
I looked behind me,
-who the hell is he
talking to.
And it was absolutely
magical between
-the 2 of us, absolutely
magical.
Don't you think men
really like intelligence
-more when it comes
right down to it.
Ahh please, are we
going to go back
-to that? Are you kidding?
Sure, it's a brain, you
know.
No man has ever
-put his hand up a
woman's dress
-looking for library
card.
[laughs].
Everyone watched the
Carson Show.
And when Carson said to
me you're going to be a
-star, my life changed.
[music].
And as they say at Cape
Canaveral, she took off
-like a rocket.
The Tonight Show was a
pinnacle for Joan.
And the more guest
appearances she got,
-either guesting with
Johnny or guest hosting
-for Johnny, the bigger
and stronger the career
was going and building up
and up.
And then eventually they
made her the permanent
-guest host of
The Tonight Show
-which was a big thing.
[music].
After 20 years on The
Tonight Show,
Fox came and offered me
my own show
-and Edgar would be
the producer.
Of course we said yes.
The first person I called
-was Johnny Carson.
He slammed the phone down.
I called him again, slammed it down
again and never spoke to me
-again. Ever.
I think he was
-furious, I think he felt
betrayed.
I was now a competitor.
He literally had me
-black listed and to this
day I have not been on
-NBC late night, ever.
As she drove off the NBC
lot, she lost her confidence.
Oh my God, what have I done.
It was such a bad period.
The Fox show even before we
went on the air, was just
-a nightmare. Edgar did not
like Ruben Murdock
-and Barry Gillette and from
the day we walked in.
There were fights.
About everything.
About whichever Coke
machine or a Pepsi
-machine, M&Ms or Hershey
Kisses.
Finally they called me in
on a Thursday night and
-they said you've got to
fire Edgar.
I couldn't do it.
I couldn't ahhh,
-I couldn't do it.
I couldn't do it.
The woman who asked, "Can
we talk?" Joan Rivers is
apparently through as
permanent host of her
-late night talk show.
From there, Edgar imploded,
absolutely imploded.
He didn't have Joan's
strength, he didn't
-have it.
I had a call from
-Gavin DeBecker, who is the
security company.
He had terrible news. Yes.
Edgar killed himself in
-Philadelphia.
He left us high and dry.
Everything went to
smithereens.
And he left me with no
career and a lot of debts.
Because he wasn't a good
businessman, and ahhh
-a lot of tough times.
[music].
I walked past Edgar's
pictures, I feel such
-sadness, such darkness.
First off, Mother I'm very
very angry at you.
Since Daddy died, you have
not spent one minute at home.
Melissa and I, we started
immediately going into
-therapy, separately and
together.
And then we did something
which sounds so sick.
We did a movie about
Edgar's suicide where
-we played ourselves.
Are you angry about
-something?
I'm angry about a lot of
-things, okay?
Okay.
It sounds so stupid and
corny, but I think by
-walking through it again
it absolutely mended us.
Totally mended the
relationship.
Don't ask, I have to go
to another doctor to
-figure that one out.
[music].
Thank you, thank you.
Have some fun.
Thank you. Thanks again.
[laughing].
Joan. Get off your knees.
Oh Joan, I worship you.
Get off your knees.
Joan, Joan, Oh My God.
Joan Rivers everybody.
[clapping].
Billy sent me this for
Opening Night.
Wait, wait.
Polly wants a
-fucking cracker.
Give Polly a
-fucking cracker now.
[laughs].
Old lady on the cover.
Young people, young festival,
young ideas, old lady.
Get ready. Hottest ticket, isn't that
great?
And the front page.
[cheering and clapping].
The play went beyond my
wildest dreams
-in Edinborough.
We had great reviews,
-the audience adored it.
But who knows what's going
-to happen in London.
It can turn on a dime.
[sirens].
Where are we?
The signage is going up.
Look your canopy
is going up.
Oh isn't that sweet.
All right.
This is where we'll make
the decision to whether
-or not I'm going to
try to bring it to
-New York.
Oh if the reviews are bad,
we're dead.
We finished it and it was
wonderful, but it will
-not go to New York.
Joan this is _________
Design.
I got a soft pink, I don't care
what it says.
Joan didn't want to open the
play in New York or LA
-because even if it's
great, they will not
-give her the Kudos
that it's great.
Because of who she is.
There is nothing she
-can do that will be
industry embraced.
How much does it hold?
Ahhh 393. So it's 400.
Yeah, 400.
I've never in the
-critics drawing.
I've always been
-considered a comic and a
Bushboy Comic
or a Vegas Comic.
There is always an
-adjective before my name,
and it's never a nice
-adjective.
I go back to Fun City
-which was my first play
in 1973 and they were very
harsh to it.
[music].
It was horrible and I will
not go throug that again.
I moved us out of
New York.
I said when that play closed
we moved right after Fun City.
I just think they are not
going to like us.
And I didn't spend all this
time and all this energy to
have us close and it breaks
my heart to see it die here.
It won't die here.
That's only that's
-killing me.
I was thinking.
You're not going to lose it.
We won't let this go.
And I know it's your work
of love.
I really think it's good.
Okay, onwards and upwards.
[music].
Hello press, be kind.
Thank you. Hello.
Very nervous, I don't want
to go 3 nights.
I think you should celebrate
second nights,
-when you're a success.
I think anyone who celebrates
opening nights is a fool
-because you're not, opening
night is your walk to the
-execution. So I will be
very very happy tomorrow
-if all goes well and very smug.
I will throw some diva scence
-when I know I have
the power.
Right now I don't know if
I have the power.
[music].
Is that enough glitter?
Yes, oh God yes.
Plenty. Plenty of glitter.
[music].
Oh shut that stupid bitch up.
[applause and shouting].
At the end of the show
Johnny Carson, on the air
-turned to me and said,
you're going to be a star.
Vaginas drop, I did not
know this.
I'm 75 years old and I tell
you I haven't peaked.
And is why I'm going to go
out that door, the door after
-that, and the door after
that and the door after
that and the door after that.
And I invite all of you,
-come with me. Thank you.
[applause and clapping].
Whoa, okay. That was pretty
extraordinary.
All stood up,
right at the end.
In America, if it goes out
in America, but you do
-stand up all the time in
shows whether, you know,
-like you're supposed to or
something.
Here they don't.
Except for this show.
What is it? Not a triumph
until we read it
-in the papers.
Nice triumph.
We love you so much.
Thank you very much.
Sorry. You're not bothering
me. All the love that we
-have here for you.
We'll feel it tomorrow
-after the reviews.
Such a nice audience.
Thank you. Now let me ask
you, when will we find out
-about the reviews?
Tomorrow, first thing
-I'm pretty sure they
fantastic.
What does it say?
Comedy, tragedy,
-surgery and Rivers isn't
going quietly.
Okay.
The energy dips slightly
towards the end,
-that is understandable
given the star's age.
They only gave me 3
stars out of 5. Okay.
Let's square.
All this play acting
is an excuse for a night
of me, me, Joan.
She is not short on
self-pity and a
-passage about her
relationship with her
-daughter is pretty low
grade smultz, mind you.
You know.
So wrong.
Exactly, it ends in a joke
you ass.
Exactly, that's why it was
just not getting it.
Longer exposure to her
even in a small theater
betrays a husky weakness of
voice that some may find
monotonous.
But I'm thinking I don't
want to take this to
New York while we're sitting
in a taxi in New York in
-6 months, and hear this
and see this again.
Yeah.
I'm not a ______
-I don't know.
[music].
I am not going to walk in
to New York City and
-be hurt the way Fun City
hurt me.
My acting is my one
scared thing in my life
-and I will not have anyone
hurt me with that.
You can say I'm not a good
comedian,
-does't bother me.
You say you didn't like me
as an actress,
-it's killing me.
And I don't want that in
New York, but I know I'm
-an actress.
It's all about acting, the
career is an actress'
-career.
And I play a comedian.
So it's over, it's over.
No one will ever take me
-seriously as an actress.
[footsteps].
Don't be down-hearted.
Are you down-hearted?
I'm not down -- I'm just --
it's not what I thought was
-going to happen.
I thought what was going to
happen was we were going to
-sail in from Edinborough
everyone was going to love it
-and we were going to pick up
a producer and then move it
-forward and change it.
But not like and of course
-there is no Billy around.
Billy is never around for
-trouble.
Yeah.
This isn't trouble, but
you know.
Any how.
[music].
The play if over and it hurts
very much, but I gotta take
-a deep breath and start
again.
[music].
[airplane].
It wouldn't kill you to get
me another commercial.
Just remember when they come in
and ask for a man, I can be
very butch.
[laughs].
So she will do anything and
really get into it,
-like she loves it.
Okay.
Okay, if nobody has anything
else, I'm very depressed.
Bye Steve. Bye.
I don't want to retire,
I don't want to
-go sit in the sun,
I don't want to learn
-to garden,
I paint, who cares?
Hello Emily Hoe.
A pleasure to meet you.
Explain to us what you are
offering.
Yes, Platinum Rye is hired
by the ad agencies to
-plug in celebrities to
different endorsement
possibilities. Yes.
And they want to have
-a meeting with Joan and
where can we put her in.
I will do anything.
I will knock my teeth out,
-and do dentasure or
whatever it is.
I mean, she's done -
I will wear a diaper,
-I don't give a shit.
Joan has a _______ a_______ focus to succeed.
And works at it every day.
I remember once meeting with
-Richard Pryor. And I sat
with him, spent an hour with
-I said, okay Richard what
we're going to do this,
-we're going to do this,
we;re going to do that,
-and we're going to plan
on this and we're going to
-do that and he looked
at me and he says,
-Larry that's all right,
but what the fuck do
-we do Monday.
That's where Joan is.
What the fuck do we
do Monday.
What is this?
That's my thing
-I've been reading.
I am holding
-____ of all the people for
the celebrity apprentice
-that we pulled off of
the Internet.
Randy R-a-n-d-e.
Turn ons taking in a
-good movie while spending
time with loved ones
-and my beautiful puppy,
Mercedes. Awwww.
Turn offs negative people who
are unkind and have no
-respect for others.
[laughs].
Well she's going to
-hate me.
Yeah, exactly.
I'm doing Celebrity
Apprentice because
-it's face time on NBC and
NBC has not let me be on NBC
-since the Carson show.
I didn't want her to do it
I thought it was F Class
people, but it is face time,
-prime time network.
I think they would be
-stupid to put me off the
first 4 shows, so I may be
-very free the second half
of October.
I think they are not going
to throw me off in the
-beginning I'm the only one
that kinda that has a name,
-even though Donald says
these international
-known entrepreneurial
celebrities.
They had Paul Newman.
You know Billy I'm going
-to say that in the Press
Release that I was told
Paul Newman was going to
be here. [laughs].
I'm very excited about
Celebrity Apprentice
-because Melissa, my daughter
is going to be on the show
-with me.
Which means we will
-have a lot of time to
spend together.
Have you had your hair done yet?
No.
Jesus fucking Christ
Melissa, why?
It's fine.
We've got 40 minutes,
-that's more than enough.
That's more than enough.
No it's not.
For my hair it is.
Melissa red-eyed in from LA
this morning and we started
-taping Celebrity Apprentice
tonight.
You've got to stop smoking
immediately.I went to a pulmonary guy
-today. Am I boring you?
No, no, i'm listening.
I'm down to like 2 for
a day.
I'm telling you --
I know, be supporive
-that I'm down to that.
He said women reaction
-differently to cigarettes
than men
I'm down to like
2 or 3 a day.
He said more woman are dying
of lung cancer than
-breast cancer.
And nobody's discussing
-that.
So that's very interesting
I'm down to about 2 or 3
-a day. So --
Yeah, I'm just telling
-you, you're really loading
the gun.
I'm just saying, I know.
I'm just saying I know.
I'm just saying, be
supportive, I've gotten
-down to that.
He scared the be jesus
-out of me.
Great pressure is
what if she gets voted off
ahead of me?
It's going to be traumatic.
I would rather I get voted
-off ahead of her.
I know, that I will always
-hold back, I know that and
so ahhh cuz I don't want
-ever to come out brighter
than Melissa and smarter
-than Melissa.
I just don't --
I don't compete with her
at that level.
I believe that _______
and even if I did win
-she'd say she held back, but
I don't think she really could.
Okay, see ya later.
In the business you've
-have to put yourself
first, you have to
-protect yourself.
And my mother will tell
-you she only wants me to
win and then she'll do
-something without even
realizing it that is very
-destructive.
And I think it's a very
-tough dynamic, because I
think it's completely
-subconscious with her.
Open that.
It's a very nice
goodie bag.
I feel very out of place,
I'm the oldest by far.
They were all talking and chatting
and for a long time I stood by
myself.
I feel very isolated.
Well I see you also bring a
lot of that on yourself.
You don't make, like tonight
you don't make any effort
to be like welcoming.
I stood there.
Well no I'm saying you were on
your Blackberry so fast, and I
tried to introduce you to people
and you were already Oh hi,
because you get so shy and that's
people don't know about you.
Hell I wouldn't walk over to
you. Well they didn't.
But you set it up for that,
you don't realize it, that
-you do that sort of thing.
Stand ups are innately
insecure.
If you would stand on a stage
by themselves and say laugh
-laugh at me, laugh with me
I don't care and I think that
-is sort of the nature
of the beast
Overall it's just my perception
of growing up comedians
they are all very damaged,
and they need that
-reassurance, it's all a
cover.
[music.]
It's been a blood bath.
They don't play fair,
-they cheat.
So Melissa is filed
-on Tuesday and I now Joan
was very upset.
She is a snake.
Annie Duke was on the
-team with Melissa and
absolutely conspired to get
-Melissa fired.
Annie Douch, that fucking
-moron.
Would you know grab onto
-my log. Yup.
And onto my trailer,
-Anne Douch, that moron she
should kiss my ass.
She should kiss my Jewish ass.
But not with those nonkosher
-lips.
Not with those big,
-that's it.
She should kiss my Jewish
-ass, but not with those
big pig lips.
[music].
That's too rough?
So tell me, you didn't
-think it was going to
get vicious?
No, I just thought it
was at least going to
-be moderately fair.
And my concern is how
-I will be portrayed.
Because I'm more of a
-of an image issue than
you do.
So that's a little
unsettling.
It, you're going to look
very angry, they already
-said, when you left you
really called them all
-kinds of names. Um-hmmm.
So that's there.
But you all --
Why don't they cut it
-to show that I was telling
the truth.
Oh they are not going to cut
it to show that you were
-telling the truth, because
they don't care, they are
-going to show that you left
pissed off. -pissed off.
But you also came back and
you also worked and
-you also --
that's all right.
But I'm just saying --
I mean it makes you more
-interesting Melissa,
frankly.
[music].
You have done really an amazing
job. But Melissa, you're fired.
Whore, pit vipers.
I want my and I want it
now. I'm not leaving
without it.
It makes me very upset to
see her that hurt.
It wasn't even her -- it was
the frustration of the lies.
It's such a cruel business.
Sometimes I just want to say
-why in God's name are you
opening yourself up to
-such punishment?
Mine is not a choice.
Mine is ahhh -- it's like
people always say are
-you in the business?
Ask a nun why she's a nun.
That's my drive, at 4 in the
morning. I have no choice.
And that's where I was from
the time I could figure it out.
No question where I was
going, there was not drugs,
-no sex, there was no
anything, nothing til I
-got my job.
That's where I was going.
Go away.
[sirens].
[music].
We're having it's going to be
a long evening.
We're doing 2 shows tonight.
Joan Rivers, autograph?
Sure, oh my goodness yes,
of course. I love you.
Every Wednesday night when I'm
in New York
-I work at some tiny little
club where I can practice
-my act.
I just talk about anything
-and everything that
annoys me.
Thank you.
You don't get the
-recognition you deserve.
Damn right William.
Okay see, I have a fan.
And William, the minute
-your not angry about things.
The minute you're not upset
-about things.
What are you talking about?
Oh my grandson he's so cute.
That's not my comedy.
I'm furious about
everything.
Good things don't always
happen to good people,
-and I'm very angry about it.
But I didn't have the anger
-wouldn't be a comedian.
Angry fuels the comedy.
[laughter].
I hate everybody.
I hate old people.
I hate ugly children.
I hate fat people.
I hated shyness.
I hate whiners.
I hate dead people.
I even have the 3 wise men
who I hate.
I love anal sex, because
you can do other things,
-you know.
it's like, you can iron,
-you can read a book.
[laughing and clapping].
Get your emails on the
Blackberry. {laughs].
[music.].
Well right now, we are getting
a 17 foot table up the stairs.
These two guys just walked it
up 7 flights and right here.
Today is Thanksgiving,
favorite time of the year.
Favorite time of the year.
Lucy and Cooper come of course.
And then I invite my friends,
and many of them are strays,
-they are single woman or my
neighbors from downstairs.
It's sad. Why is that?
I don't know, sad that you
seem to have fewer friends
-in New York.
And ahhh, I know when
-something wonderful happens
there maybe 3 people
-I'll call.
Maybe 15 years ago there
-would have been 6 people
I call.
So many people are dying,
my God.
They'd better eat fast
tonight.
[laughs].
Oh it's cold.
Every Thanksgiving
-I bring meals from
God's Love We Deliver
-to people who absolutely
too ill to go out.
This year I asked my
grandson Cooper to come
-with me.
If can stop at an
-electronic store, his
PSP is broken.
And if you're very good I'll
buy a new one for your birthday.
Well my friend had 3 of them
and he gave me one.
That's very nice.
Well --
Is this the one he gave
you? Yes.
Does he have a single
grandfather?
[laughs].
Flip your hands.
You have great hands Cooper..
Why?
[laughs]
At God's Love we deliver.
When I started out and I'm
on the board, we would give
AIDS patients that were going
we would give them food.
And now AIDS is chronic
and I'm still delivering the fucking
food, I'm so pissed.
Do you know what it's like?
Thanksgiving morning, ding dong
-the guys opens the door,
you again?
[laughs}
This is the 3rd fucking
Thanksgiving in a row,
-buddy.
Mr. ______ leave it over there.
I'm on my way to the gym.
The gym?
You're going to die today
AIDS or me,
I'm not sure which.
[laughs].
Oh look, she's got our
awww. How nice --
Hi. I'm Joan Rivers.
My I come in?
I'm Joan Rivers, this is my
grandson Cooper.
Oh wow. Nice to see you.
Joan Rivers, the Joan Rivers
I pay the bills.
You have entertained
-me for years, Miss Rivers.
I'm so glad.
I'm a photographer.
And you can see there is
on here. That's wonderful.
Right there, I photographed
-the same drugstore for
20 years.
Every time they change the
price of cigarettes.
{laughs].
How brilliant is that?
Where was it shown, Life
Magazine. I have taken over
-a 1000 photos so, you
might even know my work.
Look up flowbox.com.
Thank you, thank you.
I can't wait to get out of
here and get home and
-look you up.
flow box baby.
The name is Flo Box.
What happened that caused
-your eye sight to fail?
I believe it's connected