- [Speaker] Here, is the answer to a dreamas old as man himself.
A giant of limitless power at man’s commandand where was it science found that giant?
In the atom.
♪[drum playing]♪
-The atom is more than a symbol lockedin its tiny nucleus tremendous energy.
In a piece of uranium, the size of a walnut,there’s as much potential energy as in
the amount of coal to fill a 100 car train.
♪[drum playing]♪
♪[piano playing]♪
Useful electricity has been generatedby the atom.
A beacon for the future and symbol of hope.
♪[drum playing]♪
The peaceful atom is here today workingwonders, providing a happier,
more abundant world for all mankind.
♪[drum playing]♪
The atomic genius in his handthe power to both creation and destruction.
-I declare with all the atomic plantsgrowing up everywhere,
I wonder if girl deep and safe in her own home.I just hope they know what they are doing.
♪[drum playing]♪
-These atomic footprints on the sand of timecan never be erased.
They point a path which leads to unparallelprogress or unparallel destruction.
Atomic power puts the question
squarely to mankind.
♪[music]♪
[bird chirping]
- [Kelly McMasters] Part of me wishes thatI could go back and unwrite the story--
of course I could unwrite my story,but I can’t unwrite the story
of what happened in my hometown.
♪[music]♪
My family moved to Shirley Long Island
in 1981
I had a pretty amazing childhood
and of small community
with a strong sense of neighborhood
and solidarity.
And about fourth grade,
that was the first time that a neighbor
got sick and went up dying.
Over the years after that,more and more people got sick
and suddenly that became more than norm.
-A three-year state study confirms the factthat there is a remarkably high incidence
of breast cancer in Long Island,but failed to uncover the cause.
The statistics are startling.
-I just assumed that there was
some kind of mysterious curse—
breast cancer, lung cancer, thyroid cancer
were really the big three.
Kids started getting sick.
It was just part of the texture of the townand really it was only in college when
someone asked, “Why are you going
home for all these funerals?"
"What’s--what’s happening there?”And I realized then that things were
a little different where I grew up.
♪[drum playing]♪
I wrote this book called
Welcome to Shirley:
A Memoir From an Atomic Town.
And when I started,I had no idea of what I was getting into.
The founding of the
Brookhaven National Laboratory.
I started researching and that was
when the mystery started to unravel.
There were three nuclear reactors
at a place up the road
Brookhaven National Laboratory.
What we didn’t know at that timewas that all three leaked
and that our town Shirley was right in
the line of fire from those three reactors.
It took me more than 20 years to understandthat I grew up in a reactor community
and I had no idea.
I suddenly sought everything
in terms of how far away
places were to nuclear reactors,
nuclear waste, spills, releases,
accidents, leaks.
What kind of cancers are and are not
linked to all these kinds of exposure.
The economics,
our governments, our taxes
and every step deeper I took,
the rabbit hole just grew and grew
and it made me understand and realizedthis was not just a problem in my hometown
but it was a problem throughoutthe United States.
[THE NUCLEAR RENAISSANCE}
As a country, since the ‘70s,we’ve been against new nuclear reactors.
As we were reconsidering our energy future,
all of a sudden, we are looking
at nuclear as something
that would save us from our energy appetite.
- [PRESIDENT OBAMA] We need more
production, more efficiency, more incentives.
And that means building a new generation
of safe, clean, nuclear power plants
in this country.
[Applause]
Because the nation that leads that
clean energy economy will be the nation
that leads the global economyand America must be that nation.
[Applause]
♪[music]♪
- In the late ‘60s and early ‘70s,
power companies were almost exclusively
building nuclear power plants.
One industry executive called it
a "bandwagon rush to nuclear power".
Everybody wanted one.
Overall in the United States, approximately250 nuclear power reactors were ordered
only about 130 of them were
actually finished,
22 or 23 of them currently shut down
due to economics
or because three miles had melted down,
which was a subside of economics.
- Nuclear power... that seemed
a real possibility,
but the terror of Three Mile Island is forcing
a hard look now at nuclear power plants
in the U.S. and 21 other user countries.
- The common myth is that Three Mile Islandcaused the end of the nuclear era,
but I bought the last nuclear reactorright before Three Mile Island.
I was in charge of that procurement
and that they were becoming
incredibly expensive—
three to four billion dollars back then
when you could build a coal plant
for 400 million.
So, what really stopped nuclear power
was money.
- Since 1974, over 200 nuclear plant ordershave been canceled or postponed,
causing energy secretary, James Schlesinger,
to warn a year ago that the nuclear option
was barely alive.
- I’m not sure when I would say the nuclear
renaissance started, but it really--
for me, it seemed to begin withthis charter about Green Technology.
- Global warming.
[Train running]
Some say irreversible consequences
are 30 years away...
30 years?
That won’t affect me.
[Train running]
-I remember very clearly the first timeI read that nuclear was green.
And I thought "That must be a typo".
- Today, nuclear energy providesone-fifth of America’s electricity.
Tomorrow, it could supply you even more.
And nuclear plants don’t emitgreen houses gases.
So, they preserve our environment.
We need to reduce our dependence onforeign energy and we also need clean air.
-There was this window of opportunity thatthe pro-nuclear lobby really seemed to capture.
♪[piano playing]♪
- Well, the emissions are the big reasonwhy nuclear power is green.
Nuclear is the only form of based-powerthat’s at 24/7 always on power
that releases no green house gases,always producing power.
It’s an industry that providesextremely good jobs and a lot of money
for the community in which they’re located,but more importantly it is a way
to help ensure that we have enoughof energy to meet our demands
which the Department of Energy thinks will be
at 28% increase in electricity demand by 2035.
We have to design how we’re gonna meet that.
Are we gonna do it by importingmore foreign oil?
Are we gonna do it by with more coaland coal mining?
Are we doing it with more gasand fracking and oil shale?
- To meet our growing energy needsand prevent the worse consequences
of climate change,
we’ll need to increase our supplyof nuclear power. It’s that simple.
- Because the cause of bringing reactor
on line is so expensive.
You have that long guarantees.The lending institutions needs to know
that if something goes wrong,
and for some reason they don’t go
ahead with it,
they’ll be somebody to back stop thatand they’ll get their money back.
That’s something that the industryneeds to have really to get
the kind of investment to go forward.
-[PRESIDENT OBAMA] We are announcingroughly eight billion dollars
and long guarantees to break groundon the first new nuclear plant
in our country in three decades.
The first new nuclear power plantin nearly three decades.
- What we’re saying is thatif he knew enough about nuclear,
that’s a little bit why you seean enormous support from nuclear
the closer you get to nuclear reactor.The people who live in communities
with nuclear reactors around them
understands what it brings their community.
They’re comfortable with it.They’re comfortable with the level of safety
and you have an over 80%.The last poll that I saw done
was an over 80% support for havinganother reactor where you already have one.
♪ They wanna know you, but I had to loveyou lot to, dat to dat, dat, dat, de, de, de ♪
- [Eric Epstein] You’d be less than honest
if you didn’t say that this community
was strongly supportive of the nuclear power.
This does not meant to be disrespectful.
This is not Birkenstock Berkeley.This is not liberal Boston.
This is Bible Belt Pennsylvania.If I could only just back up.
We never really question nuclear power.That decision was made first
in the ’50’s or ‘60s, if we’re gonnago down this path.
God, I feel like I’m in a Rob Reiner movie.My dad would drive me down to the plant
and we’d see this big clouds building outand he would assure me that they were benign.
You know, I believe my dad.My dad believed the industry.
I just thought this was a wonderfulmagical technology that it comes to rescue us.
I mean, energy independence,security independence.
We thought it could warm homesat a price too cheap to meter.
Everybody bet the house on atomic energy.
All of a sudden all of these things
came in to question on March 28, 1979.
- Could I have your attention please.There has been a state emergency
declared on Three Mile Island.
Please stay indoors with yourwindows closed.
- The Metropolitan Edison Companyhas informed us that there has been
an incident at Three Mile Islandunit number two.
Question was why we didn’t know thatby the people.
The incident occurred this morningaround four o’clock,
the safety systems function thatas they should have.
- It actually begun at four o’clockin the morning of March 28.
So, it a couple of days until peopleget a handle on what’s really happening.
- [ANCHORMAN] This entire situationseems bizarre, but it’s real
and it’s happening right now here in 1979--it’s really happened.
- The information parched upby the company is either inaccurate
or purposely misleading.
- Everything is under control.
There is and was no danger
to public health and safety.
- For the industry, one of the thingsthat occurred is they couldn’t believe
that citizens had the audacity, the temerityto call on the question their expertise.
- I don’t why we need to--we need totell you each and everything that, that we do.
- That’s what I remember creeping me out.Just the smugness arrogance.
- I’m here today to try and easethe level of panic and concern.
- I thought it was worsened with the waythey’re saying.
- Good evening, the world has never knowna day quite like today.
It faced the considerable uncertainties
and dangers of the worst nuclear power plantaccident of the atomic age.
- Within a couple of days, it becomes clearthat the community just lost trust
in the government,lost trust in the company.
- It is now apparent thatthe nuclear accident that occurred
on Wednesday morning, was a lot morecomplicated and a lot more serious
and the public was first led to believe.
- Plant officials say radioactive Xenon gasis still being discharged
into the atmosphere from the reactorthat will continue for several more days.
But is the crisis over? Once again,the utility and federal experts are at odds.
- [JACK HERBEIN] I personally think thatthis crisis is over.
If we want to refer to is as that.
- [Dr. Harold Denton] I guess my own viewis that the crisis wont’ be over
until we have a coreand a coal shutdown mode.
- How can you say whetheror not were close to a core meltdown?
- They were struggling to come to terms aswhat happened three, four and five years later
and the industry was in denial.So, they never call it a meltdown.
♪[music]♪
- Two feet under the core.
We’re now approaching three feet.
- When we finally saw the footage,it was pretty clear that it was power melting.
- We are approaching four feet.We’re now five--
- That’s something people neverreally covered with TMI.
This very trusting community.They believed in nuclear power,
they believed in their governmentand they were betrayed.
- When you talk about the renaissancethe nuclear powers, as if TMI never happened.
There has been a number of incidenceand accidents and spills and leaks
and I think it’s naïve to think and even
arrogant to postulate as the industry
does that everything is under control.
- The flame from a workman’s candle
burned out electric wires
and caused the brief failure
of the reactor’s cooling system.
- The Enrico Fermi breeder reactornear Detroit was welded shut
after a partial core meltdown.
- Five Tennessee Valley Authoritynuclear reactors
were shut down because of chronicuncorrected safety violations.
A critical cooling system failed,emergency pumps went out
and only fast actionby control room operators
kept a major malfunction from turninginto something far worst.
- Its happened again, another leakat Vermont Yankee.
This time leading to a system-wide
shut down.
It’s the third leak in two months includingthe discovery of tritium in the drinking well.
- [ANCHORWOMAN] Radioactive steam leakfrom a nuclear power plant
during the night north of New York City.
An alert was declared at the Indian Point 2 Plant,
but no evacuations were ordered.
- Inside the so called ready room
at Peach Bottom Nuclear Plantin Pennsylvania,
the guard hardly seemed readyto intercept an adversary.
- According to the government’s own data,radioactive tritium has leaked
from three-quarters of U.S.
nuclear power sites.
The number and severity of those
leaks increasing.
- [Tisha Powell] A nuclear reactor on the...
- [Eric Epstein] The nuclear industryhas got to come to terms of the fact
that they’re presiding over a technologythat by definition is added control
and I just think at this particular time,humans have to evolve to a point
where they could responsively split the _____.
[explosion]
♪[drum playing]♪
♪[piano playing]♪
-On the issue of why a nuclear power,I mean why is it here and has to do
a very much so
with the Manhattan project which wasthis crash program to build atomic weapons
in the United States during World War IIwhich was prompted by the Germans
and they worked with vision
and they found out that when you hituranium-235 with the neutron, it splits--
it breaks apart and it also createa lot of energy.
- [Robert Alvarez] Einstein sent a letterto Franklin Delano Roosevelt
warning the Germany had the scientificand technical know-how|probably to build
a weapon of mass destructionfrom atomic energy
and urge the United States to do the same.
- Scientists were very, very concerned,
so it was a matter of gettinga nuclear weapon before Hitler did.
♪[piano playing]♪
We built these laboratorieswhich may have been secret
Los Alamos,
Oak Ridge in Tennessee...
- Thousands of men and women workingon the project
had no idea
of the staggering energy they wereto release.
♪[drum playing]♪
- By the end of the war, the United Statesdid develop that
used nuclear weapons.
The war ends
The Manhattan project becomeswith the end of the war
The U.S. Atomic Energy Commissionjust changes that.
Then, came a time which is very importantI think in understanding nuclear technology.
We can continue to build nuclear weapons
the United States did.
Yeah, but what else are we gonna do.We’ve created this huge empire--
this atomic.
How do we keep our laboratoriesand keep the money flowing in.
What else could we do with nuclearother than build nuclear weapons.
At that point, President Dwight Eisenhowergave a speech
at the United Nations, Atoms for Peacewas the theme of the speech.
- [President Eisenhower] This greatestof destructive forces can be developed
in to a great boom for the benefitof all mankind.
[Applause]
- [Dr. Ernest Sternglass] We were the oneswho built the first atomic bombs
and we detonated them and we destroyedhundreds of thousands of people
in one blast in Hiroshima, Nagasaki.
And we feel guilty about a lot of these.
So, we believe that no
wanted to believe that the peaceful atomis going to atone for Hiroshimam, Nagasaki.
- Brookhaven National Laboratory was earmarkedas the Atomic Energy Commission Facility.
The government partnered with Harvardand Yale, and MIT and Princeton.
I mean, this great academic powerhousewhich will work on peaceful uses
of nuclear technology
and also to pure atomic research.
♪[drum playing]♪
- What they did was to figure outother things that could be done
with nuclear technology as a possiblecheck it out.
And out of that comes crazy nucleus games.
- Nuclear explosives for a large projectsthat are simply not feasible
with conventional methods.
Excavation of new harbors, big dams,canals created in seconds
for the tremendous energy of the peaceful atoms.
- Take nuclear devices and blow at harbors?
It would be a rather radiation
tinged harbors, of course.
- Radioactions used for food preservationsand sterilization.
- Using radiation to irradiate food
and so you could eat a potatoin three years or five years.
If you felt like eatinga four-year-old potato,
this was just another scheme.
- Even your toothpaste maybe a productof the atomic age.
♪[music]♪
- [Dr. Ernest Sternglass] Everybody wantedto do good.
All the Phoenix community wanted to seethe happy peaceful atom.
♪[music]♪
- Then there was this big scheme of,where we could use the heat to boil water
and generate electricity.
- Electrical power from the atom.Today, a bold experiment.
In future years, a reality for homesand factories and schools all over the world.
♪[drum playing]♪
- The engine that drivesin nuclear power plant is the reactor
for uranium and plutonium atoms split apart.As they split apart, energy is released.
That energy is used to in this case,hit up water.
The hot water is used to make steam thatsends to a turbine that spends a generator
that makes the electricity goes outwith the water far and wide.
♪[drum playing]♪
- The plus side of nuclear power isthere’s an awful lot of energy
in a small of material.
The hundred tons that’s in the typical reactor core can generate a power
for millions of homes for two years.
It is a very enticing technology.
♪[drum playing]♪
The ones on those rows is the byproducts.
When the atoms reactor, a nuclear coursesplit apart,
their byproduct are also radioactive.They generate heat for months to years
to thousands of years later.
There’s a lot of energy that you haveto maintain while the reactor
President Eisenhower is runningand even after it shutdown
if you don’t continue to manage to removedthat heat, that fuel--
that nuclear cord can overheatand meltdown and catch on fire
and it’s gonna work against youin disastrous ways.
The 1986 accident at Chernobyl destroyedthat reactor.
In 1991, there was a reporton Wall Street Journal that said
the Soviet Union calculated thatthe cleanup cost from the one accident
exceeded the economic benefits derivedfrom all other nuclear power reactors
operating in the Soviet Union--there were 54 of them.
The risk reward is so differentin nuclear power
that one bad day at one facilitycan wipe out decades of good days
at dozens of other facilities.
♪[drum playing]♪
- Globally, there are around 450 commercialnuclear reactors in the world.
And they produce about 16% ofthe world’s electricity needs.
France gets 80% of their energy fromnuclear reactors and Japan gets about 30%.
- In the United States, we have morenuclear plants than any other country.
There are 104, but as a percent of our power, because we were a larger country,
we have 20% of our power.
- Along with that,there are 16 National Laboratories
spread across the United States.
Many of which have their own reactors forresearch and there are 19 defense plants.
♪[music]♪
The department of energy regulatesthe laboratory system
and their reactors and defense reactors.The NRC regulates the private sector,
the commercial reactors.
[Alarm, man talking on the phone]
- This is not a technology where you takefor granted that the plants
is gonna continue to operate safely.
[Alarm]
- ... 2200 powers and slowly lower
- The reactor strip.
- It something that you have to be,may constantly vigilant about
and our inspector plays a key roleon that.
♪[piano playing]♪
- Our inspectors largely to the publicwhat they’re doing goes unobserved.
They don’t really know that they’re out there,that they’re doing this kind of work
on a day-to-day basis.
- [Paul Cataldo] We’re here everyday,verifying that the plants
were operating safely in compliancewith our regulations.
- [Michelle Catts] We were independentlyassessed how the equipment are working,
how the operators are performingand does the plant responding as designed.
We look at security, we look at how the sitesprepared for flood, earthquake, fire.
We look at how safe the equipment is,maintained and tested
Hence, if we find during any ofour inspections that the plant
is not meeting one of the NRC rulesand regulations,
it can range up to several penalties, fines.
A plant can lose their license to berequired to shut down.
And we have full capability to identifysome of the... we have to shutdown the plant.
- We try to learn from every event that occurs.
After Three Mile Island, they put in placebetter trainee for operators,
better emergency response requirements.
After 9/11, we put in place a whole seriesof security improvements,
the security barriers,
the checkpoints that you have to deal with.
♪[piano playing]♪
[car running]
- [Eric Epstein] This is the southern end.
Yes, just ... in it.The fucking backdoors are wide open.
[car running]
- [Eric Epstein] Again,this is the southern gate.
But I think the gate should be closed.I think you should be _____ here.
I think rather than put up the welcome mat,you should be telling the people
to stay to fuck away.
There it is. Nobody is in there.I mean, the guard booth unoccupied.
- All the plants are required to havewhat’s known as
a radiological environmental monitoring programand they were required to do monitoring
in the area of the plant.
They have to go out and take samples ofvegetation samples of dairy water samples,
aquatic samples--all of that
and report a data back to us
and then we will run to inspection ofthese programs on a regular basis
to make sure its leaving upto its requirements.
- [Eric Epstein] This is interesting.Every year they have to produce a ramp
which is like their environmentalmonitoring program
and it looks really impressiveand it’s glossy and you’ll go back
and you’ll see these are the resultsfrom this stat and the other thing.
Well, here’s your terrestrial garden.You know, where they grab some of their samples.
They still actually haven’t replacedthe names here. It’s kind of dated.
JP nuclear really not around,Emergen really doesn’t exist.
So, it’s actually Exelon that doesthe environmental impact assessment.
Here you grab samples ... from a plant
that emits radiation d north.
So you know, you’re gonna make up your own mind,but if you don’t look, you don’t find.
- [Eric Epstein] Now, nuclear powera lot of times and most of the times
will stay within this cage,
but nuclear power by definition isan uncontrolled reaction
and when you lose control,it’s just like a jailbreak
and a hell breaks out,and that a hell of a price to pay.
- I hate to say this, but there’s a coupleof things are gonna have to occur
for things to change probably a bad thing.You know, it seems that human respond
to catastrophe in a positive way.
whether it’s Three Mile Island,whether it’s 9/11, whether it’s Haiti,
sometimes you have to be jolted backto reality.
[earthquake, things falling down]
[Chaos, people shouting]
♪ [music] ♪
- It’s been nearly 24 hourssince the powerful earthquake
touched off by huge tsunamithat swept across Japan’s East Coast.
The quake, a magnitude 8.9 wasthe fifth largest in modern history.
- Nearly, a dozen nuclear power plantswere shut down, including one,
170 miles Northeast of Tokyo.
The cooling system failedwhen the electricity went out.
- Tonight the crisis has taken another turn.We’re in the middle of covering
a full blown nuclear scare in Japan.
There are 17 nuclear power plantsacross that nation
54 separate nuclear reactors,
one plant in particular thoughis in trouble.
The Fukushima Plant...
- [Anchorwoman] Japanese authoritiesdeclared a state of emergency
at that nuclear plant damaged by the quakeas radiation level spiked.
- [NBC Anchorwoman] Japanese officials saythey have lost control of two reactors.
The fear is those reactors could be headedfor a meltdown.
- [Fox Anchorwoman] Hydrogen explosion hasbeen reported at Japan’s Fukushima Daiichi lant,
three people have been hurt,seven are now missing.
- [CNN Anchorman] The concern here,of course, is spread of radiation.
People were saying what exactly,what exactly is a meltdown?
- With the big push lately to restartour long stalled expansion
of America’s nuclear capability,
this Japanese disaster causing some realconcern and soul searching, should it?
- March 23rd, it is March 23rd isn’t it?
The day’s are all kind of bondingthe other, right now.
It’s almost two weeks after the disasterin Japan.
The news continues to get worse over there.
We’re sitting here in New Yorkand there are stories coming out
every time you turn aroundabout Indian Point
Could it happen here? What are the risks?
- Nuclear Power. I don’t want Indian Point.I’ve lived down the street.
It’s like a cul-de-sac and I’m just the--I don’t want that anymore.
How can we, how can we get themto take that away.
- But governor, we have to know--
- For 10 years, river keeper has been watchingIndian Point from the standpoint of safety.
- In fact, even one NRC official said thatif we had the chance to re-license that reactor,
knowing today, we probably would notlicense that reactor.
-Yeah, yeah, that’s not this--as the kids say "no brainer"...
- Before the Japan earthquakes,people were not paying attention
to the risks of accident,risk of radiation releases, now they are.
- Is Indian Point safe?
New Yorkers are anxiously askingthat question as Japan reels.
Tuesday, the nation’s top nuclear watchdoggave a qualified answer.
- We believed with based on allthe information we have now
that Indian Point continues to meet ourstandards and operates safely and securely.
- The problem is that to some,the standards aren’t tough enough
that the Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
The agency has granted Indian Point numerousexceptions of safety rules at the site
which sits to stride two faultlines.
♪[piano playing]♪
- Indian Point was built at a time when we didn’t understand
how big the earthquake risk really was.
They estimated that the worst earthquakethat we would have in this area
would be a 3.0 quake on a Richter scale.
The research done by Columbia Universityshows that there’s not one but two fault lines
that cross about a mile north of Indian Point
and we learned that we could havea 7.0 earthquake.
Now, the people who are in Indian Point say,“We can handle a 6.0 earthquake.”
So, not only are they running a dangerous plant,but they can’t do basic math
because the 7.0 quake is 30 timesmore powerful than a 6.0 earthquake.
The Nuclear Regulatory Commissionrequires in the United States
a 10-mile radius evacuation plan.
- [John Robin] Regulators told Americanto state 50 miles away
from the stricken Japanese Plant,but the evacuation plan here
only has a radius of 10 miles.
- Indian Point is 34 miles northof Times Squares.
There’s 20 million Americans who liveand work within 50 miles of Indian Point-
you certainly wouldn’t have a prayerin an emergency where like Fukushima
you need to evacuate 50 miles.
- The plants owners and its opponentsagree on this point
there is right now no feasible planto safely and quickly evacuate
20 million people from a 50-mile danger zone.
- [Jim Steets] I would anticipate thatthere’s a situation,
a reasonable scenario at Indian Point thatwhatever, you know, whatever warranted.
- This is one of the oldest plantsin the country.
It’s near more people than any other plantin the country.
It’s the plant with the greatest earthquake risk
and it’s got no viable evacuation plan.
Well, guess what, the relicensing hearingis in the fall of 2011.
♪[music]♪
- The stakes are really high right nowbecause so many of these plants
are coming out or about to come outfor relicensure.
♪[drum playing]♪
When they were first built,they received a license for 40 years.
If it’s relicensed, typically for 20 years,
these reactors then will be 60 years oldand the technology is aging.
Simply the parts are aging.
There are reactors where there are leakingthings into the ground and the water.
♪ [music] ♪
- Currently, Indian Point isin that process of license
we know there is hearings coming up.So, that process can work itself out.
♪ [music] ♪
- A license at these plants, it’s up toheadquarters and the courts
and the hearing process.
- So, let’s look at the licensing process.
Do they study whether or not theevacuation plan is still viable?
Hell, no.
Are they gonna study the earthquake risksat Indian Point during this licensing process?
Are they gonna study the fire risksat Indian Point?
No. They already decided that that’s okay.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Robert Alvarez] The Nuclear RegulatoryCommission is under a lot of pressure
to not push forth safety upgrades that will require additional capital expenses.
And instead, they’re being pushed to moveto goal post.
It’s kind of like, the NFL were to move the goal post at a 50-yard line
because most of its players were agingand a lot of them need hip replacements.
♪ [drum playing] ♪
- Every single plant that has appliedto be re-licensed has been accepted.
Even Vermont Yankee,
a plant where they had a collapsed at thecooling tower for God’s|sake still re-licensed.
♪ [drum playing] ♪
I don’t think they have a stampin their office for license denied.
Now, in the wake of Fukushima,they better order that stamp.
Because so many people are gonna tellthe Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
We demand you consider earthquake risks.
We demand you consider evacuation issues.We’ll close this plant.
[bird chirping]
- In case of amount of radioactive iodineleaked ...
have turned up a water samples as faras waste at Massachusetts.
There you go, bud--the friendly atom, spreading his love.
[phone ringing]
- Hello.
- Is this Irish television?
- Yeah, let’s do noon?
I’m expecting some autograph discfrom Bono.
- So, it’s you. It’s Eric Epstein.I’m calling from Harrisburg.
[Laughing]
- Yeah, I had been a busy man.
- [Eric Epstein] At one point,you were saying you have identified
elevated levels of radiation.
On the other side, you’re sayingthat you know, no increase levels
where radiation were found.
- You can’t have
- [Eric Epstein] You know, everybody keepstalking about the half-life of radiation.
We should probably start aboutthe half-life of memory.
[Laughing]
Because I mean, I got to tell you,absolute distractions in Japan
people are willing to buy the ...
-[Eric Epstein] I am expecting a news crewout here.
I’m just wondering the estimated timeof arrival because I have another crew
coming as well and I didn’t want themto get into a death match
for my media profile.
- All right. Rose, you’re not in this. Get--hey, hey, go. Go. Go. Go. Okay.
We’re taking him to the Chinese buffet.
- Okay, and today, we’re at the32nd anniversary--
- [Eric Epstein] It was 32 yearssince the accident began.
- In ’79, you didn’t have the 24/7 news cycle.I think one of the differences today
is that there’s a boat load of informationout there, but also a conflict of facts.
♪[music]♪
- [Jack Spencer] They need to geta power source to ensure
that they continue floodingthat reactor with water.
And over a couple of days, it willcool down and it will be fine.
- Hmm, okay. Well, Jack Spencer,we are all crossing our fingers
that you are right.
Thanks for joining us.
- The device to cool the fuel rodshas been dysfunctioned
and at one point in time, the water leveldid start to fall and the fuel rods
were exposed above the water.
- Nobody in the Japanese public is beingexposed to doses of radiation
that would even be close to harmful.
- Radiation has spread from these reactorsand the level seems very high.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Ann Coulter] Radiation in excessof what the governments says
are the minimum amount you should beexposed to.
- All right.
- [Ann Coulter] They’re actually good for youand reduce cases of cancer.
- The column is entitled a glowing reporton radiation.
♪[music]♪
- [Eric Epstein] Radiation just seemsso abstract.
For the most part, you can’t see it,feel it or taste it.
So, it adds to what I would callthe maniacal nature of threat.
I think people more comfortablewith the tactile image, you know,
with the aura of fire or somethingthey can see, a flood, earthquake.
- [Eric Epstein] When you’re runningfrom the invisible,
there’s a psychological component to them.
It’s almost, uh, almost a terrorbut the fear of the unknown.
- [Eric Epstein] So, we take the windand the density,
you will find that’s where we putour monitors.
We now have a very sophisticated radiationmonitoring network.
Our commitment to the community is never,ever again will you be dependent
on the government or the industryfor radiation readings.
We have innovated a new monitorwith a router hooked up to your computer
so that we could just go and takethe information on a real-time basis.
You know, the industry and the governmentseemed to think this is a settled matter
and what I’ve always said and I knowpeople bristle when I say this,
radiogenic cancers take decades.
You know, not all of them but some of themtake decades until they manifest
and you can document.
And basically, I think the government,the industries throwing in the towns
so that nobody was killed at TMI.
- [Eric Epstein] I think everybodyin the area knows somebody
who has had cancer and suspect thatit’s been linked to TMI.
When you start talking about nuclear powerand health effects,
it makes people uncomfortableand it should because there is an access.
There is a connection.
Exposure to radiation is not a good thing.Every exposure is a potential overexposure--
that’s reality.
You can make any regulation you want.
You can create any number you want,but you cannot refute what is known
and that is getting exposed to radiationis not healthy.
I mean, most nuclear power plants leak.They emit radiation on a daily basis.
This is a fact of lifebut it doesn’t excite the same kind of
outrage as other technology.
You know, nuclear power is moreis of stealth health threat.
You know, it happens incrementallyand happens slowly and because of that,
I think it’s difficult for peopleto get their arms around.
- So, you look at me and not the camera.
- [Dr. Helen Caldicott] Okay.
- We won’t hear my voice on this.
- [Dr. Helen Caldicott] No. Um-hmm.
- You can try and incorporatemy question here, okay.
- [Dr. Helen Caldicott] Okay.
- Let’s spill in. We can stop if--
- [Dr. Helen Caldicott] Let’s go.
- Okay. So, what’s your nameand what do you do?
- Helen Caldicott. I ran around the worldlike a chick without a head.
♪ [music] ♪
- We now have a group of doctors calledphysicians for social responsibility.
We’re going out, giving grand runsin Yale, Harvard--allover,
teaching the medical professional aboutthe dangers of nuclear power and weapons.
I spent my life much of it running aroundthe world worried about radiation...
People who lived down their in those houses...are dying of cancer.
They’re dying of cancer causedby that plant.
- [Dr. Helen Caldicott] No radiationis safe and a ready background radiation
produces 20-30% of the cancerwe already see and always has.
♪[music]♪
And I’m a pediatrician, I have to ...oathto save lives. That’s my vocation.
I’m an outside being a medical nunand I will keep it going until I drop dead
I suppose.
On my tombstone they can write, she tried.
- [VP Metropolitan Edison Co.]Yes, the situation is under control
and yes, we know what we’re doing
and shortly that’s the plant will be...
- [Conversation on the TV] Are we sayingthis is a complete meltdown?
All these conflicting reports they saidno water in the reactors,
but now they’re dropping waterin the reactors.
I guess, the truth is maybe,maybe the secretary is right.
Maybe we don’t know that you have...
- Mankind is so incredibly stupid...incredibly stupid.
- [Conversation on the TV]...very serious situation.
It is growing right more gram by the hour.I think we have to act accordingly.
- Building 63 hectareson a north quake fault, their nuts.
- [Conversation on the TV]I think you’re right.
I think the biggest problem we have theAmerican public is our deficit of knowledge.
- My nickname was almost Henny Pennybecause it was Henny Penny that,
that story my father told me he wentto tell a king the sky was falling down.
So, guess what,
I haven’t done it because they called me Henor Henny Penny in my family,
but that’s what I’ve done,isn’t that funny?
- It took me years to get my head aroundreams and reds.
Red is a physical dose of radiationif you get an x-ray.
Ream is the absorbed biological doseof radiation what it does to the cells.
What people don’t know is that a singlemutation in a single regulatory gene
caused by a single alpha particle.
- There’s a whole variety of radiationand it’s imperative people understand this.
Their x-rays which will which we’veall been aware of
and we’ve all been radiated.
Never had an unnecessary x-rays.
I had two CT scans the other dayat the insistence of my doctor daughter.
[Laughter]
And I got--I’ve got 22 reamswhich is a massive dose
and she said, “Don’t worry mom,you’re too old now to get the cancer."
"You’ll die before you get it,"which made me feel very much reassured.
[Laughter]
Then, there are gamma rays,which are like x-rays non-particulate
they go straight through your body.
They don’t make your radioactive,but in the instant, they go through.
They can mutate a gene.
♪[piano playing]♪
Then this alpha radiation,which is particulate emitted
from a nonstable out from a geneatom-like plutonium, like uranium.
♪[piano playing]♪
They don’t affect you if they landon your skin, but if you inhale them
or ingest them,
and they land in various organs,the surrounding cells that tiny particle
get a huge dose of radiation.
Most die, but as radiation decreaseswith the square of the disease
on the periphery of that volume of cells,the cells remained viable.
They regulates your genes, become mutatedand the cell years later instead of dividing
into two in a regulated fashion, makestrillions of cells and that’s a cancer.
♪[piano playing]♪
Then there are beta particles--American say beta.
I say beta and their electrons,which is smaller than alpha particles
do the same thing damage genes.
So, later you may incubate cancer,some 2 to 60 years later.
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Dr. Caldicott] Each dose of radiationyou receive is cumulative.
It adds to the risk of you getting cancer.No radiation is safe.
These isotopes from T9, Tc, cesium 137, radioact dividing, plutonium, tritium.
Tritium is a really nasty substance,is radioactive hydrogen.
It is absorbs through the skin and that isemitted all the time from reactors.
♪[piano playing]♪
- You would hear the statement thatno weight level of radiation is safe
and there’s radiation in the soil.
Tree of bananas.There’s radiation of bananas.
You fly to Denver, you’re gonna getradiation at very small levels
the likelihood that you would develop canceror some other disease from radiation
exposure is extremely small.
It goes up based on the amountof radiation you’re exposed to.
- [Dr. Helen] How can they say in someoccasion exposed people to radiation.
They know damn well it’s gonna increasethe incidence of cancer.
Have they ever seen this person die of cancer?Do they really know what this is about?
- [Kelly McMasters] Most people at my age,don’t assume that they’re gonna get cancer
and that was revolutionary to me thatother people didn’t live with that fear.
When I was around 10, when it startedthe first inkling that something might be
wrong there on every block people weregetting sick and sicker.
Something wasn’t right.
- [Randy Snell] I came here to have my family,live in a country setting, out on the,
you know,| pristine area of Long Island.
- Where did it go?
- When my daughter Lauren was 3-1/2 years old,we got the result that she has this cancer
called rhabdomyosarcoma that, you know,I never heard of.
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Randy Snell]As they say in the hospitalyou won the unlucky lottery.
Over the next year, we spent at least twoout of every three weeks in the hospital.
My daughter went through 11 monthsof chemotherapy and six weeks of radiation.
Her friends were--the kids on the floorand, you know, from time to time,
we would lose one of those kids.
It was hard. It was hard watching kids dieand knowing that you know that,
you could be the next person in thatsituation could be extremely difficult.
And these kids--we don’t know what we lostwhen we lost them.
You know, what future they have,but they never had a future.
- [Lauren Snell] I have my friendsin my chemotherapy.
- So you finish your chemotherapy?
- Uh-hmm.
- Are you glad to be done with that?
- Uh-huh.
- [Randy] I could remember one day saying,all I wanted to see her do
is get on the bus and go to kindergarten.
That’s how long I was lookingin the future for her.
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Lauren]I started to talk to some of the nurses,asking them about cases of rhabdo.
I had looked up the figures and it said thatrhabdomyosarcoma only happened
in one in four million kids a year.
This was a list of the kids--this is up to 20.
There was two kids on one streetwho had rhabdomyosarcoma.
The statistics on that is just improbable.
If this is so rare, there’s somethingthat’s wrong about this.
I actually called the doctor, who wasdoing an initial study on rhabdomyosarcoma.
He related the disease to exposure to low level radiation.
I said, where could she be getting thisfrom around here?
[bird chirping]
- [Kelly McMasters] So right now,we’re standing on Carl’s Industry
that was nicknamed death row.
Pretty much almost every houseon the street
had somebody who is sick with canceror something else.
People started realizing that they weren’tthe only sick ones.
Their neighbor is sick as well.
- [Randy] We would be into people’s basementsand their kitchens and we talked about
what we found and you know, we do researchand somebody would find something.
- [Kelly] All signs seemed to putto what was beyond this barbwire fence.
[bird chirping]
- These are all rhabdomyosarcoma cases.
Here is my daughter. Shirley here, all theother cases are all within the confines
of real close to Brookhaven NationalLaboratory.
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Randy]I knew there was a laboratoryat Brookhaven
But I pictured this as a bunch of guysin white coats with test tubes,
heating them up and you know,doing whatever type of experiments.
- The Brookhaven National Laboratoryconducts sophisticated nuclear experiments
producing an enormous amountof deadly waste.
- [Randy] The only research I had so thatmy daughter’s cancer was caused
by low level radiationand Brookhaven National Laboratory
was the only source of that.
♪[music]♪
- The lab is said to tap primary undergroundwater supply from 1.3 million residents
of New York’s Long Island.
- [Robert Casey] It certainly not a riskto people outside of the lab.
- [Randy] What was explained to me is thatwe’re the scientific minds out here.
We know what we’re doing and you need totrust us that we wouldn’t do anything
to intentionally harm you.
- [Kelly] I remember this moment whenit started to really snow ball.
- We recently visited some of the parentswho are dealing with their children in cancer.
Please welcome, Mr. Randy Snell to the show.
[applause]
- [Kelly] Randy seemed to be the one whomost often talked to the press.
He was a great source of dignityand his story really hit home for me.
- How many surgeries did she hadto go through?
- [Randy] She went through five surgeries.
- At that point, I decided to jointhe group called
"Standing for Truth About Radiation."
Now, you know, we had a--an organized force
To try to lobby, to bring attentionto what was going on
and it incorporated to some of the morepowerful people on the east end of the island.
- [Alec Baldwin] I think that people either"A" on the most ignorant level
looked at Brookhaven like any othernational laboratory and thought,
you know, the wonders of science you know,which should probably be the name of film
they showed me when I was in third grade.
And, and if they don’t think thatthey just think it’s just gonna be
too much of a hassle to find out the truth.
♪[music]♪
- [Kelly] Over the years and yearsof researching this,
I kept hoping that I would finda piece of paper that would say,
“Oh, you’re reading everything incorrectly,”
or actually responsibility was taken.
- We did find tritium in the ground waterabove the drinking water standard.
We determined that the extent of the poolis well within the site boundary
so no one is drinking the contaminated water.
- [Kelly] They kept saying, you know,
on The Montel Williams Showor in the press releases
that there was no off-site plume,but very clearly this states in ’91
off-site tritium plumessouthern and eastern releases
a radioactivity from a seweragetreatment plant.
The HWMA and the landfills have beendetected an offsite residential wells.
Offsite residential wells.
Area of concern 23,here and here, offsite tritium plume,
which they say does not exist.
I will just stress again,it’s like I typed up this document.
This came right out of their library.
- [Alec] You could have respect for science.
You could have respect for all the worksthat is being done BNL,
but what you can’t right offis they are liars.
The people who runBrookhaven National Laboratory
were filthy, no good, low down,scam sucking liars.
♪[music]♪
- [Randy] Brookhaven Lab had beenleaking for years.
This is in the water that we’re drinking.
I mean
We are all hooked up to the aqua for hereand the
Right, you’re bathing in it,washing your dishes with it
I think of my daughter, Lauren.
We moved in when she was a month old.To save money, we got the powdered formula.
What did we mixed the powdered formula with?
We mixed it with the water from the taps.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- [Lauren Snell] It’s so dangeroustexting while walking.
I just knew I was--knew I was definitely different.
I knew, you know, going to the hospitaland having surgeries wasn’t normal.
And I couldn’t dance with this,the one guy I love in the world.
- 1 and 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6...
- [Lauren] I still wonder why is something so...awful could happen to a person
at such a young age, you know.
I didn’t asked for it when I was young.I didn’t smoke.
I didn’t--I didn’t do anything that wouldattract cancer and my dad became my hero.
Although he wasn’t a doctor, or an oncologistor radiologist,
he...he still was able to make a differencein trying to figure out what was going on.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- [Randy Snell] All I ever wanted wasfor Brookhaven to admit that
they did something wrong,which they never have.
When they decided not to reopenthe High Flux Beam Reactor,
to me, that was an admission of guiltthat you should not put a nuclear reactor
on the source of water fortwo and a half million of people.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- [Randy]Sometimes you can’t ignorewhen you get hit in the face
And that’s what I felt we were being--
we were being hit on the facewith all these cancers.
People call me a crusader, an activist,I was being a father.
Somebody tries to hurt your child,you stand up against them and you protect them.
♪[guitar playing]♪
[car running]
[chattering]
- The energy is holding its meetingwith the public at least annually
where we describe our assessmentof safety performance,
I didn’t mean ... for the prior year.We also had a time...
- Once a year,even the Nuclear Regulatory Commission
has to show up and tell us witha straight face, ”We’ve got your back.”
I bet that’s their least favorite dayof the year.
- Let me tell you I have never seena situation in which a regulatory agency
deserves what it’s gonna get tonight
as much as theNuclear Regulatory Commission deserves it.
[applause]
- You know, nuclear power people tendto feel very passionately about it
and so that does translate in the kind ofreception we get from the public.
- There are agents in the backso if there is an firearm,
just stand up and make your wayfrom the north ..., those exits.
Thank you.
[chattering]
- We see the day to day activity.Certainly, we don’t make policy.
But in our small role of inspection,assessment, event response,
very critical role,
so we welcome the opportunityto have dialogue with members
of the public because they’re importantstakeholder as well.
- And the bottom line for thisassessment meeting is,
in 2010, energy operated in ... safelyand that’s all the ...
[people shouting]
- ... feeds into these indicatorsare provided by energy
the inspectors verify this informationon every performance indicator.
In summary, in any point operatedsafely of the...
[people shouting]
- Hold on for a second.
If you don’t allow them to speak,we won’t get the opportunity to speak.
So we need you to respect usjust like we respect you.
[people shouting]
- Quiet.
- If you continue to
- And in the interest of peoplewho want to speak,
we would change our agenda here[applause]
and we will hold the next...to questions and answers.
- Fukushima, I’m sure, it means just like this,where the government told them,
nuclear power very safeand we see what happened.
[applause]
- You’ve granted in the section exemptionfrom the sent fumes rule number two,
which you know it has crack in it,you know it’s leaking tritium
in to the groundwater and in to the...but you’ve exempted the ...
- I’m here to remind you that your jobto protect the public, not the interest of
[cheering and applause]
- You guys are supposed to have our backsand if you want to go back
in... regulator,
you better wake up tomorrow morningand find a new gear
because this will not ...
[cheering and applause]
- [Michelle Catts] Anytime the liaisonbrings me anything,
I question "What they do?""Is this the right to do?"
"Is this the safe thing to do?"
Is this, you know, piece of equipmentgonna work if you consider size
and make eventual leaks or--
we are always questioning everything they doand I really wish that they could see
what we do on a day-to-day basis.
How important it is for us to keepthis plant safe
and I live eight miles in the plantwith my family.
You know, it’s very important to us too.
- [Eric Epstein] If you like in the NRCto the local cop on the block
and everybody liked the local copon the block
and most NRC people I know I like.
But they can only be as effective,and aggressive as the mayor lets them
and in this case, the mayor is the senate.
♪[drum playing]♪
- [Neil Sheehan] The congress is very involved.They wanna know what kind of inspections
we’re carrying out to make surethis plant is safely operated.
So, they have a very keen interestin making sure that we’re living
to our responsibilities.
Then, congress decides on annual basis,how much money we’re actually gonna get
and congress is going to decidewhat our key priorities are going to be as well.
- [Peter Bradford] What you have isthe process in which the nuclear industry
gives a lot of money to congressand spends a lot more than that on lobbying
and that results in a lot of pressureon the commission.
- [Arnie Gunderson] The only thing you can dois hold the regulator responsible.
And the problem is that the regulatorsresponsible for congress
and congress is being run by lobbyist.
- The Nuclear Energy Instituteis the mouthpiece for the industry.
Now, they’re very good at what they do.They just don’t spend money,
they spend money in a smart wayand they get tangible results.
♪[music]♪
The nuclear power industryis the best example of how money
and power intersect to impact policy.
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Robert Alvarez] These agencies--the Energy Department,
the Regulatory Commission are riddledwith a lot of conscientious, smart,
well-meaning people who are in a systemthat if you do go outside of the boundaries
of what they considered good form behavior,you’re on a career path nowhere.
♪[drum playing]♪
- In late 1990’s, there was a whistle blowerwho had basically found and reported
that the owner of the Millstone 1 reactorhad been engaging a very dangerous practice
of pulling out it’s spent fuelfrom the reactor before it should.
The Nuclear Regulatory Commission
did what you call "wire brush inspection"and ordered them to shut down.
This really angered a lot ofRepublican members of Congress
that a regulator would come inand do something like this.
And the one member of congresswho was particularly outrage,
who was in a position to dosomething about this
was Senator Pete Domenici.
- [Pete] I came from a state within New Mexicoand you see out there people
some people thinks it’s a desert.
Besides that, it has two giant laboratories.
♪[music]♪
- They got indoctrinated nuclear powerwhich put me into the probably
most committed senator to bring back inthe nuclear power
and to bring it back like whythe Eisenhower spoke of it
when it was first done.
- He led the effort to introduce legislationthat would cut 700 people
from the payroll of the inspection programin Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
♪[drum playing]♪
- [Andie Gunderson] Pete Domenici wrotea book and he actually laughs
about bidding off on the NRCand he said he has threatened their budget.
- [Peter Bradford] He had to come to Jesusbeing with the chair
and Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
From that point on the NRC becamean enabler rather than a regulator.
- [Shirley Ann Jackson] In recent monthsas many of you have stated that NRC
has been the subject ofa number of external reviews.
Some of them sharply critical from ourcongressional appropriations committees.
Most NRC observers are call in fora more rapid move
to a regulatory framework with licenseeafforded more flexibility
in meeting more requirements.
- So, you had a prominent senatorwith over site capacity
who have the ability to take awayaggressor regulation
and did the NRC essentiallyhas become a pussy cat.
It’s really a toothless regulator.It has no bite.
- [Shirley] In fact, we have invitedthe nuclear energy institute,
NEI to submit to the commissiona petition for rule making outlining areas
where it feels NRC regulationsare duplicative,
unnecessary in light of other rulesor not sufficiently risk in form.
- When you think of NRC, you’re thinkingyou know, probably about
an aggressive regulatory protocol wherethe industry is accountable to the NRC.
This is upside down. The NRC is madeto be accountable to the industry.
[wind blowing]
- [Joe Cosgrove] The village ...right adjacent to Braidwood Nuclear Plant.
It was always a joke, you know,you live next when you get a plant
as everything close, it gonna blow up.
I used to look at thatas kind of a chicken little syndrome.
I mean, that was irrational, becauseI thought all the safeguards were in place.
You see water going in, water going out.I never had any concern for it
because of my assumption were thatit was so heavily regulated.
- [Kim Cole] I would sit outsideand I would listen to the hum
and it would be soothing to me.
And I would just sit outside likein the middle of the night
and I would listen to the hum of thatand be comforted by it.
I thought that was a good thing.
Since then and my knowledge of it,I don’t find them comforting at all anymore.
I find them the biggest and hugest enemy.
♪[guitar playing]♪
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Joe Cosgrove] I was gonna ask aboutthe socio-economic area
and trying to be nice to prettypoor community.
I just always believed with waterand people--
It doesn’t really matter how muchis in your wallet
or in your bank to get the same rightto clean and safe drinking water.
- [Joe Cosgrove] When people called meand asked me
"Is it safe to drink our water?"I couldn’t answer that.
I’m a Park District Director.
We went to theIllinois Environmental Protection Agency.
They didn’t have the authority to goon station property
that was the NRC, which is we need to findthe answers of what could possibly get out
to harm people.
So, we started testing.
-[Joe Cosgrove] When you talked aboutan old shit moment,
I think I’ll be using a file that I havecalled "Pioneer Environment Tritium" file
October 31 to 2002, shell a well numbertwo 496 picocuries tritium per liter.
This was a ground water well similarto what another 260 people
in this community were drinking from.
That was my first inclination thatthere could be an issue with radionuclides
with the plant.
Then, I found on the other side of the plant,there are 200,000 picocuries per liter.
♪[guitar playing]♪
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Mick Scheck] Right there you could seethe plant, great view, falling the trees,
could grow taller.
- First, I learned about tritiumin the nuclear leaks and stuff like that
was basically in the newspaper.
Exelon stood with conviction from day onethat you have nothing to worry about,
blah, blah, blah.
- [Thomas O’Neill] The tritium amountsthat are in the ground
are of such concentration that they are lowand they are not a health hazard to you.
This tritium is not in the drinking waterexcept for one well.
- [Mick] Exelon started buying our properties.They bought up a few and it didn’t take
them very long and all to the bulldozerdown the ground.
There was a scary thought it’s so safeand great,
why you bulldozing the perfectlygood house.
My gut instinct at that point was, oh, shit,you know, what have they really done to us.
♪[drum playing]♪
- [Shirley Cavanaugh] This again isthe Kankakee River
and this is the discharge mine.
This is going over tothe Braidwood Nuclear Station.
♪[drum playing]♪
- Irene and I were talking and one ofmy neighbors have recently passed away
and then when I was telling her aboutall my neighbors,
she started telling me about all her neighborsand we’re only a mile and a half apart.
- [Shirley Cavanaugh] This were allthe cancers are,
there is ... or there is ...,
there is Cavanugh, there is Jennings,Trembi, Delrose, Cunning, and Bruckman,
all in a row--
everyone of these homes without missinga house had cancer.
♪[drum playing]♪
- This is absolutely no coincidence.It just that go cancer, cancer, cancer.
This is not a conincidence.Something is wrong, definitely wrong.
- [Shirley] Both of them died of cancerand actually there’s more right behind them.
There’s a driveway that goes back here,the lady dying...
- We honestly thought thatour Health Department and the NRC
and places like that were looking out for us,but we’ve also found out that the NRC
and Exelon are working togetherand that’s their job to convince us
that everything they’re doingis perfectly safe.
- [Steven Orth] Good evening,my name is Steven Orth
and I am the representative from theUnited States Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
- [Joe Cosgrove] Public meetings we heldwas a chance for people to ask
the people that really are chargewith their protection, questions.
- [Mick] It was not a good vibe in therefor them at that point
and I always felt the same way.
The NRC, they supposed to be thereoverseeing these guys to protect us.
- NRC requirements allow licensesincluding nuclear power plants
to release radioactivity intothe environment.
We require that the releases be controlledand monitored
and that the resulting radiation dosesbe below the limits that we’ve established.
- [Joe Cosgrove] I was never aware thatthey were allowed
or permitted to discharge radioactive fluid.
If you would have asked anybodyin this area 10 years ago,
they would have laugh at you, say,"No, there is some government agencies"
"and state agencies to protect us.They would never let that to happen."
- [Mick] When we looked more into it,we found that their hands were actually
basically tied from being able to doanything other than sit down
read reports that say everythingis safe and great.
- Why is it Exelon doing the testingof these wells
and why isn’t there an independent companydoing the testing?
- The licensee is primarily responsiblefor operation at its facility
and for identifying and analyzingwhat occurs at their facility.
- [Mick] Our opinion of the NRC thatthey sit at their desk,
Exelon goes out and does all these tests
and stuff like that and they write uptheir paperwork and they bring it back
and they are like,"Look we got an A+ on their report."
Guys, look at it and look it all fallswell within the guidelines and stuff.
File that back to the drawer,“Where are you taking me to lunch today?”
- We can assure you that the contaminationalthough locations are not originally intended
does not present hazard to public healthand safety.
- We wanted them to say, “Hey,you know what? We’re gonna help you now.”
They didn’t do that.
They consistently told usthe water is safe to drink.
♪[drum playing]♪
- We found out that the leaks actuallyhappened as far back as 10 years prior.
- [Mick] They say there were 250,000 gallonsin ’96 that leaked at one of the vacuum brakers.
In ’98 was a six million gallonsand in 2000 was like three million gallons
according to them.
- We were knowledgeable of the 2000 leak.The 2000 leak was reported by the licensee
in their annual radiological release reportwhich is public document available
to anybody in this room,available to anybody on this panel.
- You’re telling me that the US NRCknew of the 2000 tritium leak in 200?
Is that what you said?
- I’m telling--I’m explaining that|that leak is a matter of public record.
- It’s a matter of public record becauseI’m going to the US NRC representative
that I have a letter from who told methat they have no knowledge.
And so I wanted to make sureI can quote you tonight
that you state that you were awareof the 2000.
[cheering and applause]
- [Kim Cole] One of the issues of tritium water.Like I say, you can’t smell it,
no can’t see it, you can’t feel it,but it is absorbed--our water is not safe.
♪[drum playing]♪
- We’re not third world.
We are America and we should be ableto turn our water faucet
and that you’ve got safe drinking water.
We have to get in our vehicleswhether we’re young, old, disabled,
and we have to go and get water, filledin jags and I should not have to do that.
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Mick] We wanna, you know,just one move away from this, you know,
and we never really kind of getthat opportunity to do.
We’ve almost been held hereas nuclear hostages
because it basically tells you,no, you’re not affected
and we’re not gonna be buyingyour properties.
I’m afraid it just looks like ...you know and you’re just, you know,
you’re collateral damage, and itkind of sucks to be the collateral damage.
♪[piano playing]♪
- The NRC’s regulations had beenon the books for decades
saying that you’re not allowed to havea drop of treated water,
leave a plant except via controlledand monitored pathway.
Not a drop, yet they foundmillions of gallons
that leaked out from plantsand haven’t find anybody in ...
- We try to put things in contextin terms of the risk significance.
Tritium is a weak beta matter thatgenerally, it will pass through
the body, pretty regularly.
We also always talk about the fact thatthis tritium will dilute to obviously
to get in the nearby river or I mean,the delusion factor will come into play as well.
♪[piano playing]♪
- [Joe Cosgrove] When you get upin the morning,
you have to drink a water,brush your teeth.
You make an assumption thateverything is fine.
Somebody is taking care of that waterSomebody’s testing it,
it’s safe for me, it’s healthy,until you start finding out things.
Things that terms stakeholderswho are stakeholders
You know all people,we are the primary stakeholders,
you know, we’re not in this for profit,we’re just here to live.
♪[piano playing]♪
♪[music]♪
- [Alec] Nuclear is clean energy.Nuclear it’s clean energy.
Clean burning nuclear powerand you’re like,
"what the fuck are you talking about?"
Nuclear power is too, too,
Do they make the nuclear rods come offthe nuclear rod tree?
We go pick them from the nuclear rod orchard?
- [Kelly] Ultimately, this nuclear storycomes down to waste.
Even if something works perfectlyand there are no leaks, no spills,
no accidents, we’re creating multitudeefficient products--
strontium, tritium, cesium and all of thesehave a profound effect on the human body.
A lot of these efficient products havehalf-lives from 10 years to--
plutonium has half-life of 24,000 years,
however half-life is different than whenit is no longer dangerous to human interaction.
When you take that into consideration,it turns into 240,000 years.
- It has been estimated thatby the end of this century,
one-fourth of the country’s energy outputcould be derived from nuclear power.
Before that could happened, some way mustbe found to get rid
of deadly radioactive residue forever.
- Let me put it to you this way,would you buy a house from a developers
who said I’m gonna put a toilet in,but there’ll be no septic system for 30 years
and we’re just gonna let the human tarpspile up in the front yard for 30 years.
Alright, the nuclear tarpshave been piling up in the front yard
for 30-40 years.
Nobody I know wants to live next toa high level radioactive waste site.
We didn’t sign up for that. We signed upto the near nuclear power plant.
- Here, in Idaho for example, barrels ofradioactive waste are merely covered up
with dirt, while the nearby nuclear reactorcontinues to churn out still more waste.
- [J. Samuel Walker] A waste was an issuefrom an early stage of the Manhattan project.
But at that point, of course, doing theManhattan project,
the focus was almost exclusivelyon building a bomb
and waste was a problem for later.
♪[drum playing]♪
The commercial nuclear power industryboomed in the late 1960’s
to everyone’s surprised.
- Scientists estimates that withinthe next 10 years,
nuclear power plants will be turning outa railroad powerful of radioactive waste
every 24 hours.
- The atomic energy commission suddenly fellunder a great deal of pressure to find
a site for a high level wastefrom power reactors.
- The atomic energy commission wants to buy2000 acres of land near Lyons, Kansas,
were used as an atomic wastedumping ground.
- The favored solution at that timegoes salt.
- Scientists believed the vast depositof salt out here will make
an ideal containerfor radioactive materials.
- You put the waste on salt depositthe salt kind of envelops the waste
and then it’s safe.
So that was a theory of that point.
- The AEC conducted its ownenvironmental impacts study
and concluded that yeah,Lyons looks pretty good.
- After several years of research,the AEC ...the plan was safe.
After radioactive waste could bepermanently sealed and buried.
- Unfortunately, Lyons, Kansas,to turned out not to be the place.
While Lyons residence didn’t objectto the project,
scientists at the University of Kansas did.
They were not convinced block formationabove the salt mine,
where the nuclear waste was to be buriedcould withstand the extreme heat generated
by the radioactive materials.
And in the end, the site turned outto be extremely unsuitable
and it was the rocket sciencewho figures it out.
The AEC could have known about that,should have known about it
and simply didn’t know its homework.
♪[music]♪
The advent of nuclear technologyhas created another problem
what to do with the tons and tonsof radioactive waste.
♪[drum playing]♪
Congress has ordered the Department of Energyto find a stable underground location
to isolate the waste from everythingand everybody for 10,000 years.
Finally, in 1982 congress, said, well,we have to find a solution to this problem,
so here what is it.
DOE is going to investigate sitesand find three other suitable
and recommend those to president.
There’s all kinds of public oppositionand the area surrounding these three sites.
No, state wants to take nuclear wastethat stage radioactive for thousands of years.
And therefore, the process is not workingand so we’re going to designate a single site
and that that site, of course,is Yucca Mountain.
Scientists are gambling that Yucca Mountain,an hour and a half drive northwest of Las Vegas
is the perfect spot to store the nuclear wastebecause of its remote desert location.
If you talk to the Nevada people,they will say screw Nevada Bill,
they didn’t have the clout to stop thesite in their state from being designated.
- Nevada Senator, Harry Reid,says Yucca Mountain isn’t about science,
it’s about money.
- [Sen. Harry Reid] This is alla brainwashed job
from a very powerful industry.
The nuclear power industry is as goodat throwing money around
as anyone I’ve ever seen.In fact, I think they’re better.
♪[drum playing]♪
- The US government moved closer todayto make the Yucca Mountain in Nevada
be the underground storage sitefor this country’s nuclear waste.
As expected, the president Bush todayapproved the Yucca site.
- With the president and congress on board,billions of dollars already in the underground
using Yucca Mountain to store nuclear wastemight seem like a foregoing conclusion.
♪[drum playing]♪
♪[piano playing]♪
- The Obama Administration has been clearthat storing nuclear waste at Yucca Mountain
is off the table.
The 27-year-old project seen its budgetslashed by congress in the past several years.
- [J.S. Walker] As I understand thatPresident Obama
instructed Secretary of Energy to withdraw it.
- Energy secretary Steven Chu said thatscientists have learned more about
the repository, making it less of an idealoption to destroy the country’s nuclear waste.
♪[drum playing]♪
- [Robert Gibbs] Taking Yucca Mountain offthe table, in terms of a long-term solution
for a repository for a nuclear waste,is the science.
The science...
- [J. S. Walker] There are concerns abouttheological issues,
especially seismic issuesand for Senator Reid,
this is a strong opponent of Yucca Mountains.So, I think that’s the main reason.
- And have the President ... out of his budget,
It is a dream come true for so manythousands of thousands people in Nevada.
- Now, the Nuclear Regulatory Commissionmust decide if it wants to restart
what is already a 25-year, $14-billion project.
A former staff of Senator Reid,Greg Jaczko, now chairs the NRC.
- [Gregory Jaczko] It wasa difficult decision,
and because it is sucha controversial program,
but again, it was one that was madeand I believe in the best interest of the agency.
♪[drum playing]♪
- Until the court cases are resolved,or until something else happens,
there’s no progress at all.
- The waste now is on site at the hundredand so nuclear power plants
that are generating power in this country.
♪[drum playing]♪
- I think that America now has a futurefor more nuclear power creation.
I have no problem with that,as long as the ... is created.
That is a power.
If it is safe for 100 yearsand by then, they will have some way
of taking care of it permanently.
- The Japanese government has releaseda bleak picture of the fall out
from the accident at the Fukushima Daiichi Plant.
The new survey measures levelsof radioactive cesium 137
is soiled near damage the facilityand it shows the spread
and seriousness of the contamination.
- The survey confirms the appallingmagnitude of the contamination.
I was hoping I’d be able to return somedayto spend my last years in my hometown,
but the maps suggest even thatwon’t be possible.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- Japanese prime minister Naoto Kan says,Japan needs to review its nuclear policies.
He aims for the country to become a leaderin new energy sources after the nuclear crisis
at the Fukushima Daiichi Plant.
- Germany’s government agreed this morningto phase out all of its nuclear power plants
by the year 2022.
It’s the first major power to becomenuclear-free since the disaster in Japan.
- Celebration in Romeis antinuclear protesters marched
a big win, an ends to the country’snuclear program.
As you can see, in the square behind mepeople behind me are celebrating
a resounding defeat to ...who just two years ago,
was saying that nuclear powerwas the future for Italy.
Clearly, what happened in Japanhas encouraged people to say
that they didn’t want nuclear power here
and that is why there was such a massiverevolt against what was told 95% of that.
- [Kelly] I really thought about withina week after Fukushima,
okay nuclear renaissance off the table.
- In light of what’s happened in Japan,I would like to hear what you believe
President Obama’s position is nowon nuclear power,
generally in the United States.
Does he still support a rebirth of nuclearpower and construction of new plants?
Could you just give us your best estimateof what his position is?
- The present budget is what it isand we’re asking for long guarantees.
That position has not been changed.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- So, that’s a yes.
- That’s a yes.
- Good.
That’s what I wanted you to say,so if you just said yes, that easy.
Now, with regards to the loan guarantees,given again what’s happened,
do you and the president, want the congressto support the full 36 billion
that you had put in the president’s budget?
- Yes.
- Okay. You’re learning.
[laughing]
- You’re not a not noble prize winnerfor nothing, I guess.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- [Joe Cosgrove] I’m a common person.I really don’t wanna label putting on me.
I don’t feel I’m an activist.I don’t feel I’m anti-nuclear.
I turn on the light switch.
I wanna pay a reasonable electric bill.
I have questions if it should be builtnext to our people, live, drink.
If they are gonna build more of these reactors,it all boils down to the issue
which was trusting the agenciesand trusting the industry.
How are they gonna do it differently?
Do you really learn from your mistakes?
That’s my major question right nowat this point of time.
♪[guitar playing]♪
[car running]
- We should be worrying aboutthe entire range of problems
that opposed by an aging nuclear fleetthat is a 20th century technology
that looks pretty scaryon the 21st century world.
We need to continue to pushthe Nuclear Regulatory Commission
to protect the public from true risksnot to keep this industry operating.
- The NRC always had critics--probably always will.
People wanna know could the nuclear power plantin their community be affected
the way those Japanese reactors wereand they wanna know
what their federal regulators doingto ensure that it would not occur.
- [Gregory] I fully expected they’re goingto be lessons that we’re going to learn
and likely because of those lessons,we’ll be making changes to the way
that we do business and the waythat the industry does business.
The safety of these plants is our foremost task.And I think if you look at the operation
of most of these plants,the track record has been pretty good.
I think the overseer of the NRC has playeda big role on that.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- I’m not here for the money.I’m not for sale.
I’m here because our community was affectednegatively by nuclear accident.
I’ve been doing it for 31 years,so I don’t get rich doing this
nobody’s paying me to do this.
What I wanted to do and this has happenedquite frequently is that after Fukushima,
a lot of attention has been refocusedon nuclear power.
There’s a lot of people here I know.
Most of who I thought would bein prison by now,
but I think we’re all one community.
I don’t view as being antinuclearor pronuclear-- we’re procommunity.
I just think it’s time for us to face upbe adult as they look.
We’re not mature enough as a civilizationto harness the atom.
Maybe sometime down the road, but not now.
We have the opportunity to do it differently.
To do it correctly. To do it cleanly.
We chose not to and that’s because there’san intersection on money and politics
and it meets at your local nuclear power plant.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- [Kelly] They’ve never said I’m sorry.
They’ve never admitted to beinganything but a good neighbor.
If they don’t understand what they didto Long Island, then how can we communicate
the possibilities are.
What the possible risks arefor the rest of the United States
if we start building nuclear reactors again.
We all lived down the downstream from something.Really, the only thing you can do is learn
about what you’re downstream fromand try and protect yourself from it.
The only thing that makes menot completely hopeless, is really my son.
When I first became pregnant, you know,one of the big question is where to raise him?
And when we found the perfect place,it was one of the few counties
that I’ve ever come across that it doesn’thave anything that comes up on the APA’s search.
I thought yes, this, this is whereI can happily and safely raise him.
♪[guitar playing]♪
- But again, it’s that bolder on ... feeling
that the invisible somehow will lacethe air that I breathe,
the water that I drink.
It just feels like any moment,it’s gonna walk up my driveway.
♪[guitar playing]♪
♪[music]♪
♪[drum playing]♪
♪[piano playing]♪