We as a country should move forward
and learned everything we got.
- If--you know--you allow women to work and get modern
and get modern and get educated
you lose your culture and your heritage and your deep-rooted values.
- But i don't agree.
- If we want India to develop--i think all of us have to change.
- We have to change the mentality.
- As much as I love and respect my culture
I think of myself as a very modern young girl
and i want freedom.
♪ [background music] ♪
- Thank you!
- This is no place for little girl anymore.
- This is a place for women.
- Everything you say
you say it with shonest
with your enunciation
with your smile
with your confidence.
- Is that that's makes a winner.
- Always be groom well.
- If your in this profession
you need to take care of your self--
I mean--you know--you need to invest in yourself.
- Make me believe that you're gonna be model.
- Make me believe that she is going to be
a bollywood star.
- You know what I mean?
- The connection.
- The humanity that comes out of you.
- The judges are just 70 people sitting
in a row.
- But the people that are already cheering you all
are the people behind them.
- And the judges get influenced.
- If I was a woman and I had a gunt
trust me my boobs would be automated
but would be out.
- And I would be looking at the mirror--
Ok--I'm in the final ten.
- How I'm gonna look.
- How I'm gonna present myself.
- Four hundred people infront of me.
- The whole world watching me
eyes on me.
- In India you got one--over a billion plus population.
- It's a billion and a half now.
- To be a Miss India and be considered
the most beautiful girl in India.
- And that's should takes
the exposure.
- Whose gonna give them that exposure?
- They get ads.
- They get films.
- They get contract.
- Just to have the television exposure.
- Whose gonna give the five whole minutes?
- You know what it cost for an ad
for five minutes or five seconds?
- This is not an Indonic exposure.
- They get Singapore contract.
- They get Hong Kong.
- They get Middle East.
- They get England.
♪ [background music] ♪
- I'm going to make full use
of this platform.
- Because I think that in Miss India
would give me the identity
that I deserved to have.
- My own identity.
- Because you know in our society in India
its dominated by men.
- For a woman to have her standing in the society
its very important for her
to go out own for herself.
- You are for yourself.
- You live for yourself.
- You gain respector.
- You absolutely.
- You gain respect.
- Put your hand in your lap like that.
- Let take it from the dog.
- Really?
- And action.
- [Ruhi] Hi I'm Ruhi Sighn.
- I belong to the base famous spin city of Jaipur.
- I have done a lot of beauty pageant.
- Then I know one
I never gone first in my life ever.
- But I will make my parents really proud.
- They created me--I'm their creation.
- That's what I believe.
- As they created me
its my duty to walk as hard as possible
and--you know--just to make them
feel that--yes--the creation is good--
you know.
- You just not added some risk
into the enlightment.
- It's--it's something worthwhile.
-I love everything in my life
and I'm here to make my parents
really proud of myself.
- So guys--watch out for me.
- Will take it from the top all it can be???.
[pedal cart ring] [vehichle sound]
- ♪ [background music] ♪
[faucet splash]
[glass sound]
- [Ruhi's mother] Jaipur is no place for Ruhi.
- I'm very happy at least she go.
- She's not like outside world
European countries.
- Her goal is saving for future
- What ever she want to do she will do it.
- It's not like ???
- I'm not talking about Mitch the general girl of registrar.
- Most of them ???
- They are not allowed outside the house.
- All of women or girl should have some--
some freedom
but no.
- Do whatever she want to do--do.
- I'll always supported her.
- Me and my husband.
- [Ruhi] Hi! I'm Ruhi Sighn of the spin city of Jaipur ???
- I'm a dancer now.
- Basketball team now.
♪ [background music] ♪
♪ [prayer hymn] ♪
[whoosh]
[foreign dialogue]
[demonstrators chant]
[exercise music]
- Up up up go!
- And now try not to be like elephant
for loud ???
- Up up up.
- Sixteen.
- Seventeen.
- Eighteen.
- Nineteen.
- Twenty.
- Five.
- Four.
- Three.
- Two.
- One.
[dance exercise music]
- Stand!
- Stop step.
- When you enter
you stop
and turn your torso.
- Stop step.
- Move back lean 90 degree.
- Stood walk and don't.
- Back straight.
- Not your hand.
- Elbow front.
- Chin turn on.
- It hurts?
- Yah!
- It looks favs.
- Chow.
- Second.
- Third.
- Fourth.
- We have beauty all along.
- But then we've learned how to control that beauty.
- How to make that beauty even fine.
- You added a speech and diction expert.
- And then you added someone
who could act to teach you how to walk to ramp.
- And to how to better your skin
and straighten your teeth.
- And now its become a little ah
a little factory.
- I mean its a manufacturing unit
when you go inside
and you polish like a diamond
to the best that you can be polish to.
- That's it.
- You've modern Indian woman.
[crowd chanting]
- The Pantaloons Femina Miss India World 2009
is contestand no. 15 Poojah Chopra
[crowd claps]
- The first pageant I went for was a school pagent.
- After winning that
it went on to larger like
Miss Poona and Miss Residency Club.
Miss India Queen and Navy Queen.
- So it then come to National level.
- See non Miss is unlimited.
- Once you ??? on the house
you won a bungalow
you won a mansion
life goes on.
- That's a gradual progression.
- And I think you should be like this
because when the time you don't dream
you would not know where to impart.
[stair sound]
- Yah! That's it.
- That's lovely.
- Look at that!
- Stunning.
- [Poojah] A lot of people feel
that fashion degrade woman
because its more about of a external beauty.
- But I feel it has not only about external beauty.
- It's give a platform to a woman
and more than anything
fashion like this give her the courage
giver her the confidence.
- She has an identity to how I was now.
- It changed you.
- It changed everyone prespective about you.
- You change from a person
you become a personality.
- I become punjacho from Miss India
which make a lot of difference.
[crowd chanting]
[camera click]
[foreign dialogue]
- [audience] Poojah!
- And she's really beautiful you know.
- A lot of hardwork without resign.
- She deserved [crowd chanting]
[whistle blown]