- [Cara Waters]Good afternoon,everyone
and welcome to Smart Company’sfirst webinar of the year
which is “How to Deal With CustomersWho Won’t Pay”
I think you agree it’s apretty important topic for all S.M.E.’s
My name is Cara Waters,I’m the editor of Smart Company
and today I’m joined with our--virtually
because they're in a differentplace from me.
But Andrew Baird, who is a Principal in Accounting and Business Advisory at WHK
and Emily Jaksh, whose task isHead Guru at HR Gurus.
So for the webinar, if you haven’tlogged in to one of these before,
just to let you know, the way toparticipate is firstly by listening.
The audio will automatically bestreamed through your computer speakers,
and another way is by Twitter.
So you can use the @SmartCompanyor the #smartcowebinar.
Now the major way though if you wantto get really interactive
is to ask questions via the questions pane, which is,
you’ll see on your computer screens.
What you’ll do is you type in your questions
in the space at the bottom and click on send.
I’ll then be asking our two presentorsAndrew and Emily all your queries.
So I really encourage you to sendthem through because--
it is an important topic and somethingthat I’m sure a lot of you
do have questions about.
Also, I just want to thank ourpartners for today’s webinar, who--
business victor –which is Business Victoria,
providing big help forsmall business.
And one final reminder before I hand over to Andrew and Emily is that,
you don’t have to worry aboutfuriously copying down notes
because we will send you copyof the slides to the webinar
and recording of the webinaras well.
So you can relax a little bit, althoughyou're free to take notes if you want to.
So, I'll now hand over and let themintroduce themselves properly
to Andrew and Emily.
- [Andrew] Great! Thanks, Cara!My name is Andrew Baird,
I'm a principal with WHK[unintelligible]
and we specialise in not going [unintelligible] S.M.E. market.
- [Emily] And my name is Emily Jakshand I'm also with the S.M.E. market.
[unintelligible]
- [Andrew]And today, [unintelligible] gonna betalking to you all about
How we deal with customers who won't pay?And it's [unintelligible] and [unintelligible]
First of all, we gotta be talking about[unintelligible] but [unintelligible]
How to avoid [unintelligible] and tipsfor making customers coming right back
and [unintelligible] deal [unintelligible]